<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://william6542.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://william6542.github.io//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-04T21:21:54+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Bibliothēca Williamae</title><subtitle>William's digital library. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Wormwooddiariesassignment</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2023/06/04/WormwoodDiariesAssignment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wormwooddiariesassignment" /><published>2023-06-04T08:58:58+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-04T08:58:58+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2023/06/04/WormwoodDiariesAssignment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2023/06/04/WormwoodDiariesAssignment.html"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html xmlns:d="http://W10-Wormwood-Source-WW.xml"><head><title>Wormwood Diaries</title><link rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="W10-Diaries-WW.css"/></head><body><h1><span class="title">Wormwood Diaries</span></h1><h1><span class="author">Emma Wormwood</span></h1>
    
       
        
    
    
    
    
        <div>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 1]
        </span>
            
            <h2><span class="date">January 28th. Tuesday.</span></h2>
            <p>Got up early. Pretty day, –thawed considerably. Had full <span class="place">school</span>. Good lessons. After supper had discussion on "Negro" and "Indian" question. Laughed about <span class="name">Dollie</span> and me goin' (Gowin). <span class="name">Roy</span> ate an onion, and I went in the other <span class="place">room</span> and drew map of <span class="place">Italy</span>. Beautiful night, not very cold. Went to bed early. I rode <span class="place">home</span> from <span class="place">school</span>, <span class="name">Jennie Dyer</span> and I stood up.</p>
            
                <h2><span class="date">January 29th. Wednesday.</span></h2>
               <p> Pretty day. Had good <span class="place">school</span>. <span class="name">Lou</span> went <span class="place">home</span> at last recess. They laughed about "<span class="name">Scratch</span>" bringing <span class="name">Rose</span> home. A. class drew map of <span class="place">Italy</span>, on board. In <span class="name">B. Geog</span>. I asked how high is the highest <span class="place">peak</span> in</p>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 2]
        </span>
            
                <h2><span class="date">January 30th. Thursday</span></h2>
                <p>Had good <span class="place">school</span>. Sunny in the morning – clouded in afternoon. At noon <span class="name">Irwin</span> and <span class="name">Roy</span> tried to see who could act the "biggest monkey." Rode horse, rubbed him down, jumped rope (buggy line) and so-forth. <span class="name">Lou</span> and <span class="name">Lillie</span> fixed minutes of last evening Society met. – Turned <span class="name">Lillie</span>'s watch back with mine. – <span class="name">Jesse</span> laughs at me about being always hungry. <span class="name">Nellie</span> and <span class="name">Mary</span> went to <span class="place">church</span>. <span class="name">J</span> called us "Back woodsers" I replied, that I would rather be</p>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 3]
        </span>
            
            <p>a "backwoodser" than a "heathen". We went down to the <span class="place">school</span> house. Not many there; had no meeting. Went to Mr. <span class="name">Strate</span>'s. Had music. Laughed at <span class="name">Joe</span> and <span class="name">Charlie</span> about going to "Hunt"('s) <span class="name">Charlie</span> has concluded he would rather Hunt than fish, so he's not been lately seen going up the <span class="place">creek</span>. – We suppose it is because the fish are all "Young." When we started home it was raining. <span class="name">John</span> <span class="name">Dollie</span> and I came across the <span class="place">pasture</span>. (<span class="name">Dollie</span> thought we were going to <span class="place">China</span>.) <span class="name">Joe</span> asked what I had been saying about Kentuckians. <span class="name">Peek</span>'s brought <span class="name">Mary</span> and <span class="name">Nellie</span> home. <span class="name">John Whitehouse</span> was converted. (<span class="name">John W</span>. came to <span class="place">school</span> this evening for <span class="name">Lou</span> and <span class="name">Lillie</span>.</p>
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 4]
        </span>
            
            <h2><span class="date">January 31st. Friday.</span></h2>
            <p> Dark and rainy. Had twenty pupils. <span class="name">Irwin</span>, <span class="name">Walter</span>,<span class="name"> Charlie</span>,<span class="name"> Roy</span> + <span class="name">John</span> went down the <span class="place">road</span> and came back after <span class="place">school</span> had called. <span class="name">Roy</span> and <span class="name">John</span> tried themselves. –I was doubly kind, in my actions, but, inwardly, I burned with anger. After <span class="place">school</span> I traced pencil marks in register. As I started, I asked if I had made any missteps, or done the least thing to cause such actions as had transpired. The reply, "Nothing. Not a thing, they just took a notion to be mean." A I came across the <span class="place">bridge</span> I sat on the banister and watched the water flow over the rocks. I read the Modesto paper. <span class="name">Jesse</span> tried to make us believe he could not read. After supper he brought up "scripture</p>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 5]
        </span>
            
            <p> argument; read two chapters from the Testament, asked our opinions, then gave us his explanation. Calls us "backwoodsers." We went to bed early. <span class="name">Lillie</span> did not come to <span class="place">school</span>.</p>
            <h2><span class="date">February 1st. Saturday</span></h2>
                <p>Dark and gloomy. Wish I could be at <span class="place">Nilwood</span> to the <span class="place">Local Institute</span>. I straightened up books and papers, put most of them in my valise. Had a talk with <span class="name">Nellie</span> about <span class="place">school</span>. (a perfect jewel, to be so good.) I fixed my tan skirt. <span class="name">Jesse</span> went to Modesto. <span class="name">Roy</span> cut wood. <span class="name">Mary</span> baked all morning. (Had baked chicken for dinner, and I ate so much dinner that I was not hungry for supper. <span class="name">Jess</span> said it was the first time he ever saw me not hungry) <span class="name">Ed</span> came in the evening. He got letters from <span class="name">Mamma</span>, <span class="name">Ida</span> and <span class="name">Katie M</span>. got school journal and circular from supt. <span class="name">McClure</span>.</p>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 6]
        </span>
            
            <p>told about hauling one ([[note in parentheses above  -- Jermin?]]) of my pupils around in the big wagon. Laughed about him going to <span class="place">Carlinville</span> on Tues., following the wagon-ride. <span class="name">Joe</span> came home with <span class="name">Jess</span>. Argued about "Back woodsers" and "Mountain heathens". They said <span class="name">Dolly</span> got mad. The boys went to <span class="place">town</span>. As they were starting, <span class="name">Joe</span> was going to make me take back something; I made a certain remark which caused him to take sudden leave. Gave us oranges. <span class="name">Dolly</span> and I went to church with <span class="name">Ed</span>. Roads were very bad, and we went through the fields. <span class="name">Rhoads</span> preached, but got sick and <span class="name">King</span> took the meeting. Excellent meeting. Got home about eleven. Boys came before we went to bed. After noon <span class="name">Lillie</span> came to tell us about going over</p>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 7]
        </span>
            
            <p>to <span class="place">Scottsville</span> to wait on her sick cousin. Wanted <span class="name">Dollie</span> to take her part in the dialogue. Asked <span class="name">Dollie</span> to bring her books. (Rocking chair proved to hold two)</p>
            <h2><span class="date">February 2nd. Sunday.</span></h2>
            <p>Rainy and dark. <span class="name">Jess</span> went away. <span class="name">Charie Crawford</span> came. I read story of "<a href="https://openlibrary.org/works/OL33139547W/Howard_and_his_teacher_the_sister%27s_influence_and_other_stories?edition=key%3A/books/OL45016028M">Howard and his Teacher</a>". Laughed about "Love in the Kitchen"; also "Love in the Front-room." ("I'd get it and keep it".) <span class="name">Roy</span> and I took down items; and <span class="name">Joe</span> started for the book, I screamed, jumped straight up and ran in the bed room. threw the book to <span class="name">Roy</span> but <span class="name">Charlie</span> got it. They went in little bed room to read but we would not let them alone: they went out by the milk house and read, then gave us the book. <span class="name">Mary</span> called on everybody to help put the hogs in the</p>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 8]
        </span>
            
            
            Irwin Baptist is 16 years old today.  
            
            <p>lot. <span class="name">Dolly</span> went to put <span class="name">Joe</span>'s hat on him and had to stand on the bench. Had dispute as to whether pancakes were baked, or fried: proved that bake is right. <span class="name">Jess</span> says <span class="name">Flo</span> is the only good looking girl in <span class="place">Illinois</span>. Mr. <span class="name">Essex</span>, the best looking man. <span class="place">Kentucky</span> is noted for tobacco, whiskey and and big feet. <span class="name">Jess</span> says "<span class="name">Dollie</span> is - is - is, all right." "She's too smart to be called a backwoodser." <span class="name">Roy</span>, <span class="name">Nellie</span> and I are "Smart alecks." I went to bed at seven o clock. It snowed, rained, sleeted and what not, all day. ground not at all frozen but covered with snow and sleet. </p>
            <h2><span class="date">February 3rd.    Monday.</span></h2>
                <p>Two or three inches of snow and still snowing. Trees and bushes look like Christmas trees. Snowed all day, but thawed more than it snowed</p>
            
            <span class="pb">
        [PAGE 9]
        </span>
            
            <p>Had a very small school, only eleven. Stopped to see Mr. <span class="name">Strate</span>. Made short talk about conduct of Friday. Better results, but far from perfect. At noon, the girls were getting locks of everybody's hair. (If you'll come over after <span class="place">school</span> is out, I'll give you a lock of my hair.) I was tired all day: about sick. After supper I wrote to <span class="name">mamma</span> and to the girls. Talked of suicides. <span class="name">Jess</span> said he had no sympathy for such people. Would not grieve if his own father committed suicide.</p>
            
        </div>
    
<div><h1>List of Names</h1><p><ol>
                              
                           <li>Dollie(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Roy(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Jennie Dyer(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Lou(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Scratch(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Rose(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>B. Geog(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Irwin(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Lillie(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Jesse(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Nellie(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Mary(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>J(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Strate (music teacher) 
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Joe(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Charlie(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>John(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Peek(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>John Whitehouse(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>John W(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Walter(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li> Charlie(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li> Roy(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Jess(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Ed(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Mamma (mother) 
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Ida(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Katie M(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>McClure(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Dolly(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Rhoads (preacher) 
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>King(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Charie Crawford(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Flo(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>Essex(N/A)
                                   </li>
                              
                           <li>mamma (mother) 
                                   </li></ol></p></div><div><h1>List of Places</h1><p><ol>
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    room (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Italy (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    home (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    home (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Italy (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    peak (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    church (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    creek (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    pasture (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    China (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    road (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    bridge (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Modesto (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Nilwood (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Local Institute (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Carlinville (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    town (relative)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Scottsville (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Illinois (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    Kentucky (absolute)
                                </li>
                            
                                <li>
                                    school (relative)
                                </li>
                            </ol></p></div></body></html> --&gt;]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Wormwood DiariesWormwood DiariesEmma Wormwood [PAGE 1] January 28th. Tuesday. Got up early. Pretty day, –thawed considerably. Had full school. Good lessons. After supper had discussion on "Negro" and "Indian" question. Laughed about Dollie and me goin' (Gowin). Roy ate an onion, and I went in the other room and drew map of Italy. Beautiful night, not very cold. Went to bed early. I rode home from school, Jennie Dyer and I stood up. January 29th. Wednesday. Pretty day. Had good school. Lou went home at last recess. They laughed about "Scratch" bringing Rose home. A. class drew map of Italy, on board. In B. Geog. I asked how high is the highest peak in [PAGE 2] January 30th. Thursday Had good school. Sunny in the morning – clouded in afternoon. At noon Irwin and Roy tried to see who could act the "biggest monkey." Rode horse, rubbed him down, jumped rope (buggy line) and so-forth. Lou and Lillie fixed minutes of last evening Society met. – Turned Lillie's watch back with mine. – Jesse laughs at me about being always hungry. Nellie and Mary went to church. J called us "Back woodsers" I replied, that I would rather be [PAGE 3] a "backwoodser" than a "heathen". We went down to the school house. Not many there; had no meeting. Went to Mr. Strate's. Had music. Laughed at Joe and Charlie about going to "Hunt"('s) Charlie has concluded he would rather Hunt than fish, so he's not been lately seen going up the creek. – We suppose it is because the fish are all "Young." When we started home it was raining. John Dollie and I came across the pasture. (Dollie thought we were going to China.) Joe asked what I had been saying about Kentuckians. Peek's brought Mary and Nellie home. John Whitehouse was converted. (John W. came to school this evening for Lou and Lillie. [PAGE 4] January 31st. Friday. Dark and rainy. Had twenty pupils. Irwin, Walter, Charlie, Roy + John went down the road and came back after school had called. Roy and John tried themselves. –I was doubly kind, in my actions, but, inwardly, I burned with anger. After school I traced pencil marks in register. As I started, I asked if I had made any missteps, or done the least thing to cause such actions as had transpired. The reply, "Nothing. Not a thing, they just took a notion to be mean." A I came across the bridge I sat on the banister and watched the water flow over the rocks. I read the Modesto paper. Jesse tried to make us believe he could not read. After supper he brought up "scripture [PAGE 5] argument; read two chapters from the Testament, asked our opinions, then gave us his explanation. Calls us "backwoodsers." We went to bed early. Lillie did not come to school. February 1st. Saturday Dark and gloomy. Wish I could be at Nilwood to the Local Institute. I straightened up books and papers, put most of them in my valise. Had a talk with Nellie about school. (a perfect jewel, to be so good.) I fixed my tan skirt. Jesse went to Modesto. Roy cut wood. Mary baked all morning. (Had baked chicken for dinner, and I ate so much dinner that I was not hungry for supper. Jess said it was the first time he ever saw me not hungry) Ed came in the evening. He got letters from Mamma, Ida and Katie M. got school journal and circular from supt. McClure. [PAGE 6] told about hauling one ([[note in parentheses above -- Jermin?]]) of my pupils around in the big wagon. Laughed about him going to Carlinville on Tues., following the wagon-ride. Joe came home with Jess. Argued about "Back woodsers" and "Mountain heathens". They said Dolly got mad. The boys went to town. As they were starting, Joe was going to make me take back something; I made a certain remark which caused him to take sudden leave. Gave us oranges. Dolly and I went to church with Ed. Roads were very bad, and we went through the fields. Rhoads preached, but got sick and King took the meeting. Excellent meeting. Got home about eleven. Boys came before we went to bed. After noon Lillie came to tell us about going over [PAGE 7] to Scottsville to wait on her sick cousin. Wanted Dollie to take her part in the dialogue. Asked Dollie to bring her books. (Rocking chair proved to hold two) February 2nd. Sunday. Rainy and dark. Jess went away. Charie Crawford came. I read story of "Howard and his Teacher". Laughed about "Love in the Kitchen"; also "Love in the Front-room." ("I'd get it and keep it".) Roy and I took down items; and Joe started for the book, I screamed, jumped straight up and ran in the bed room. threw the book to Roy but Charlie got it. They went in little bed room to read but we would not let them alone: they went out by the milk house and read, then gave us the book. Mary called on everybody to help put the hogs in the [PAGE 8] Irwin Baptist is 16 years old today. lot. Dolly went to put Joe's hat on him and had to stand on the bench. Had dispute as to whether pancakes were baked, or fried: proved that bake is right. Jess says Flo is the only good looking girl in Illinois. Mr. Essex, the best looking man. Kentucky is noted for tobacco, whiskey and and big feet. Jess says "Dollie is - is - is, all right." "She's too smart to be called a backwoodser." Roy, Nellie and I are "Smart alecks." I went to bed at seven o clock. It snowed, rained, sleeted and what not, all day. ground not at all frozen but covered with snow and sleet. February 3rd. Monday. Two or three inches of snow and still snowing. Trees and bushes look like Christmas trees. Snowed all day, but thawed more than it snowed [PAGE 9] Had a very small school, only eleven. Stopped to see Mr. Strate. Made short talk about conduct of Friday. Better results, but far from perfect. At noon, the girls were getting locks of everybody's hair. (If you'll come over after school is out, I'll give you a lock of my hair.) I was tired all day: about sick. After supper I wrote to mamma and to the girls. Talked of suicides. Jess said he had no sympathy for such people. Would not grieve if his own father committed suicide. List of Names   Dollie(N/A)   Roy(N/A)   Jennie Dyer(N/A)   Lou(N/A)   Scratch(N/A)   Rose(N/A)   B. Geog(N/A)   Irwin(N/A)   Lillie(N/A)   Jesse(N/A)   Nellie(N/A)   Mary(N/A)   J(N/A)   Strate (music teacher)   Joe(N/A)   Charlie(N/A)   John(N/A)   Peek(N/A)   John Whitehouse(N/A)   John W(N/A)   Walter(N/A)   Charlie(N/A)   Roy(N/A)   Jess(N/A)   Ed(N/A)   Mamma (mother)   Ida(N/A)   Katie M(N/A)   McClure(N/A)   Dolly(N/A)   Rhoads (preacher)   King(N/A)   Charie Crawford(N/A)   Flo(N/A)   Essex(N/A)   mamma (mother) List of Places school (relative) room (relative) Italy (absolute) home (relative) school (relative) school (relative) home (relative) Italy (absolute) peak (relative) school (relative) church (relative) school (relative) creek (relative) pasture (relative) China (absolute) school (relative) road (relative) school (relative) school (relative) bridge (relative) Modesto (absolute) school (relative) Nilwood (absolute) Local Institute (relative) school (relative) Carlinville (absolute) town (relative) Scottsville (absolute) Illinois (absolute) Kentucky (absolute) school (relative) --&gt;]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Puyallup Historic Project</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2023/05/15/Puyallup-Historic-Project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Puyallup Historic Project" /><published>2023-05-15T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-15T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2023/05/15/Puyallup-Historic-Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2023/05/15/Puyallup-Historic-Project.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="puyallup-historic-project--puyallup-public-library">Puyallup Historic Project @ Puyallup Public Library.</h3>
<p>Team members: William Wu  <br />
Course requirement: University of Washington MLIS Capstone<br />
Sponsorpship: Librarian Aleya Stone<br />
Time period: 2023 Jan - Jun</p>

<p>Objects processed: 590 unique objects<br />
Time spent: 140 hours (not including lunch breaks or discussions with others)</p>

<p>Current active historic archive link: https://puyal.ent.sirsi.net/client/en_US/default/search/results?te=ASSET<br />
Unfortunatley due to overwork the library manager has still not yet finalized approval for my conributions to be uploaded to the public website.</p>

<p>ID: PPL00614<br />
<img src="/assets/PPLcap3.jpg" alt="Introduction image Puyallup Tribune" /></p>

<p>In order to fufill the Capstone requirement, I started working at the Puyallup Public Library to help them continue their project of digitizing a whole room of old physical objects that come from and around the local community. This project had already been going on for a few years, however, due to the number of steps and the focus which is required of the worker, progress had been slow. Furthermore, since the project was entirely on a volunteer basis, the pace had not been steady.</p>

<p>Puyallup is a small town located on the edge of the Sea-Tac I-5 corridor. It was primarily a logging and farming area,and that history is reflected in the fact that the valley is relativey devoid of trees despite being so close to a national forest and national park. Logging and wood processing operations are still active today, though to a much smaller extent.</p>

<p>ID: PPL00630<br />
<img src="/assets/PPLcap1.jpg" alt="newspaper clipping of man killed by log" /></p>

<p>At first, I followed the established procedures for scanning, analyzing, and generating metadata for the master microsoft access data sheet. However, I eventually realized that I could add a further step. This further step was the creation of a excel reference sheet for all the unique names that occured throughout my work with the objects.</p>

<p>The reference list is important because the main users of this archive are locals, and other people who wish to investigate their ancestors who may have lived in this area. Therefore, the names of their deceased relatives, and which object IDs said relatives appear in, is a useful tool. I also predict the ancestry links (at least those that I have found) will be very useful for users. Although I was not able to verify each single person, those that I have ascertained to a high degree of certainty I have linked to in the reference sheet.</p>

<p>The investigative process of verifying if a person requires a lot of thinking and strong memory. Sometimes a person may not be verified until their spouse or child appears in a later article, and you can cross reference them. For example, if there is both a Jr and a Sr for a same name, and both ages could possibly be valid (for example a committee member of a local club), then I will not include the ancestry link, <em>unless</em> a later object has some context which can prove who is who (for example the father dies, and it says he was on this or that committee).</p>

<p>Unfortunatley, due to older social conventions in which men’s names are often used in conjunction with Mrs. to denote a married woman, I have counted said names in the “male names” tab. This is certainly unfair to the women, but it is not always the case that I can even find the full information regarding a person. Therefore, each count of a name is not tied to the actual person, but to the name. This fact is reflected in the number of names recorded for men vs women: as of now my reference sheet holds 657 male names and only 379 female names. And on top of that female names are much harder to verify. Still, I think the reference sheet is still useable for local citizens wishing to learn about their ancestors. And I hope that the reference sheet may be of some analysis value to data scientists.</p>

<p>A section of the reference list I created: <br />
<img src="/assets/PPLcap2.jpg" alt="Section names A of reference list" /></p>

<p>Another social problem was the fact that Native Americans and Japanese Americans do not appear often in the newspaper clippings, despite the fact that both had an attested presence in the area. The majority of the Native Americans were displaced in the early-mid 1800s, while the Japanese Americans were expelled during World War II. To this day, the Puyallup Japanese American population has not returned to its pre-war levels, the Native Americans even less so. Neither of these historical trends are represented in the artifacts, simply because the historic locals did not care. The only reference I found was a single cut off article on the back of a main item (since the donor did not deem that Japanese-American story important enough), about the establishment of Camp Harmony, a holding center for Japanese Americans who were to be later transffered to bigger internment camps.</p>

<p>As for the subject headings within the existing input sheet, I cannot say for certain that subject headings which I have input are all-inclusive, but I hope that what I have chosen to put in may still help users to get a picture of what life was like back then. For example, the prevelance of the subject heading “Women’s Clubs” may indicate the high level of gender segregation between men and women, and it may also indicate the much stronger social norms and bonds that tie citizens together. The large prevelance of newspaper clippings on which I have input the subject heading “church” may also indicate the higher level of religious belief or social cohesion which existed in the past.</p>

<p>One of the major problems encountered after the photos were scanned was how to sort and tag the newspaper clippings. Each photo was usually placed in an individual folder, for protection. However, the newspaper clippings were not afforded such luxury. Often times, dozens of small clippings would be crammed into one folder. Therefore, the physical assignment of IDs was very difficult, since I couldn’t simply mark the folder for each newspaper clipping, nor could I mark the clipping directly. My solution, though not elegant, was simple: I cut a small post-it note and wrote the ID on the note, and then stuck it to the back of the newspaper clipping.</p>

<p>Another issue encountered was the excessive size of a newspaper clipping: either the physical size, or the number of names, or the fact that both sides were interesting. Because microsoft access only allows so much input of characters in each value box, if the number of names became too much to input, I would have to create a duplicate sub ID with the same item in order to include all the information. For example, a newspaper clipping that was interesting on both sides would be split into PPL00997-001 and PPL00997-002.</p>

<p>Another example of a dual-item. The donor who made the clipping was clearly not interested about the spider, but I thought that spider story was funny and interesting so I scanned it and processed it as well. ID: PPL00733-001 <br />
<img src="/assets/PPLcap4.jpg" alt="Albino spider fun story" /></p>

<p>A third issue was logistical: I live in Seattle and the library is in Puyallup. The drive, when not in traffic, is relatively easy, but still long, clocking in around 45 minutes one way. The drive, when in traffic, is horrendous: clocking in around 55 minutes. I tried to work around this issue by staying as long as possible each time I went, so that not only would I spend more time working and less time driving, but also avoid traffic by leaving late.</p>

<p>ID: PPL00587<br />
<img src="/assets/PPLcap5.jpg" alt="Final placeholder photo of a logging family" /></p>

<p>The future of this project depends on the willingness of volunteers to continue it. Since the library does not allow removal of the physical items, volunteers will have to go to the library in order to work on it. While the steps for processing each object are simple and easy, the cumulative effect of the steps, and the addition of my individual persons reference sheet makes the whole process much more difficult. I hope that I can continue to work on the project if I am still around the area, but this may or may not turn out to be the case.</p>

<p>Regardeless, before I leave, I will try to write down some notes and thoughts, explain my reference sheet, and leave a tips list for the next volunteer. Hopefully the big room full of items will eventually be processed so that the users can get a more fuller glimpse into the interesting history of this town.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Puyallup Historic Project @ Puyallup Public Library. Team members: William Wu Course requirement: University of Washington MLIS Capstone Sponsorpship: Librarian Aleya Stone Time period: 2023 Jan - Jun]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Film Roll #1</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2023/04/20/Film-Roll-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Film Roll #1" /><published>2023-04-20T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2023-04-20T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2023/04/20/Film-Roll-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2023/04/20/Film-Roll-1.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="film-roll-1">Film Roll #1</h2>
<p>The film roll was shot from around 2022 late September to 2023-01-30.</p>

<p>To start things off, there is me, sitting on the roof. This was a fun self portrait. I may have sat too far away though.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 1.jpg" alt="Me on the roof" /></p>

<p>Next is a view of the Olympics on a clear day. I liked this photo. The colors are soft yet vibrant. The lighting on all components of the photo is clear.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 2.jpg" alt="View of the Cascades" />]</p>

<p>Now we switch cardinals and see Rainier in near-sunset light. This was lucky to get during the winter.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 3.jpg" alt="View of Rainier during sunset" /></p>

<p>This photo at sunrise was very cool. It almost looks like a night photo, but in fact this was taken right before sunrise. The green tint road lighting was a cool result, I am not sure how that happened, as the lights are <em>not</em> green. The cardinal is East towards the Cascades.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 4.jpg" alt="Sunrise looking towards cascades" /></p>

<p>Here is a photo from a walk during mid afternoon in October. It is near my apartment, in the old neighborhood around the ravine park.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 5.jpg" alt="Walk in neighborhood" /></p>

<p>This photo is of a dual building property that I really like. The main house behind the tree is connected to the smaller townhouse looking building by a covered walkway inside the property. It’s really cool. The colors are also interesting, yet not to jarring or flamboyant. It blends in with the trees well. This household also loves to plant flowers on the sidewalk bed during the warmer season. The warmth of the lights inside the house are not really well captured, I think I could have gotten closer, or waited until a bit darker, to really capture the warmth of this home.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 6.jpg" alt="dual house" /></p>

<p>One day I woke up to massive fog. I was quite insane. Especially so the fact that I had to drive to my intern-project work place that day. Luckily, by the time I got past downtown Seattle, the fog was completley gone.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 7.jpg" alt="fog" /></p>

<p>Now we have a series of photos from my long walk around Tangletown. Tangletown is a relatively less treed neighborhood, with wider streets, and bigger houses. It is nice, but doesn’t feel as homely or comfy as Roosevelt Ravenna. I’m not sure why it developed this way. The downtown area with the shops and restaurants also feels a lot more empty and desolate than other small downtown areas. It’s nice, but just… it feels like the streets are too big for the area.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 10.jpg" alt="tangletown" /></p>

<p>This was a lovely little cottage house hidden behind some big big trees. I tried to get the house better lit, but the light was just too strong on the trees. The shades of green are so lovely.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 11.jpg" alt="cottage" /></p>

<p>This was a cute little craftsman house. The contrast between the light teal and bright red is very fun, in addition to the big red truck framing the house.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 12.jpg" alt="craftsman house" /></p>

<p>These two houses were quite nice, on a quiet street. The color contrast with each other makes them feel like a nice duo, and their raised patios seem very nice to sit on.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 13.jpg" alt="dual homes" /></p>

<p>I liked this photo a lot, it was many shades of orange, and the car frames the house nicely.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 14.jpg" alt="house" /></p>

<p>This house is on the ring road around Green Lake. I love how the house tries to be tall like the tree, but the tree is just huge. Also it’s so well shaped lol.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 15.jpg" alt="tall tree" /></p>

<p>This photo had the feel of some old gothic story. It was really a nice area, a dead end circle. It seemed very empty though, and there were no signs of life or movement. A bit eerie.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 16.jpg" alt="gothic home" /></p>

<p>Now we switch to the UW Classics meeting room. It’s a really cool room. The students basically seem to use it as a hang out room, when it’s not being used for meetings or presentations. The lighting is not the best. There was only a <em>single</em> book on Sallust, and not even any books of Sallust’s work proper.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 17.jpg" alt="UW classics room" /></p>

<p>I messed up the focus on this photo. Whoops. This was a fun dinner at a nice Italian restaurant (in Mukilteo) with Mary. We both love Tiramasu, but we agreed that the one here wasn’t very good. The pizza, however, was <em>very</em> good. Mary was slated to leave later that month to her new job on the East Coast! Yay! I was glad for her success and new opportunity, but sad to lose a good friend.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 18.jpg" alt="Mary" /></p>

<p>And finally, this is a self image I did in my apartment. I realized I am not very good at smiling, especially when I don’t have glasses or a hat on: it just makes me look weird. So I didn’t smile.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FR2 19.jpg" alt="Me" /></p>

<h3 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h3>
<p>In general, I think this set of images came off much better than the Origin Film Roll #0. I managed to get a much better sense of lighting. However, many of the photos still had some lighting issues, and many were just not well framed, or boring, or pointless. I still have a tendancy to shoot to much, and I could still improve on <em>really</em> slowing down and thinking about my shots.</p>

<p>I found that the most interesting things to shoot were things with a sense of identity. There had to be identity in the photo, it couldn’t be just som random shot. Either a very beautiful and interesting house, or a person, or a combination of elements.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Film Roll #1 The film roll was shot from around 2022 late September to 2023-01-30.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Porco Rosso (1992) – WORK IN PROGRESS</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/13/Porco-Rosso.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Porco Rosso (1992) – WORK IN PROGRESS" /><published>2022-12-13T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-13T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/13/Porco-Rosso</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/13/Porco-Rosso.html"><![CDATA[<p>First posted 2022-12-13</p>

<p>It’s been a while since I watched a film sitting down, focused. I had intended to watch this two weeks ago, but I was busy. I watched this late past midnight, at Portland.</p>

<p>Released in 1992, <em>Porco Rosso</em> is a Ghibli Studio film about a pig pilot ace of world war 1, trying to make his way in the interwar environment. Filled with gorgeous panels and smooth animation, the film is decievingly light-hearted at first, and only rarely do the bright colors of the mediterranean dull and grow dark.</p>

<h3 id="porco-marco">Porco Marco</h3>
<p>The first thing: Marco is a pig. Porco Rosso. Rosso probably because his seaplane is red. Why he is a pig is never explained. Some reviewers suggest he is a pig because he cursed himself to be a pig after he saw his comrades die in a giant air battle. Other say he is a pig because he refuses to live in a society in which being normal means being a fascist. Still others say he is a pig because he has not accepted his the love of either Gina or Fio. These are all possible. Cause aside, I think the more interesting thing is how his being a pig plays out in the film.</p>

<p>Despite being a pig, Marco seems to be treated fairly and kindly by most other characters in the film. No one wonders why he is a pig, he’s just, the pig pilot. And even being a pig, the pirates still fear him, Gina still loves him, and Fio looks up to him and (if it can be considered love) loves him too. Clearly, looks are not everything, and looks are decieving. Yet many reviews I’ve read online imply that his pig-ness is a bad thing, they try to see under what conditions does his pig-ness break, and he becomes human again. The further implication being that <em>being human is a good thing</em>. Yet as we travel with Marco, I don’t see much trace of evil in him. He is a jolly pig, a kind pig, a smart and skilled pig. He lives well, treats others well, and flies well. If that’s all there is to being a pig, why is it bad?</p>

<p>Marco appears as a human only four times in the show. Once in a photo, which his face is partially scratched out. Second in Gina’s flashback with him piloting her. Third in Fio’s eyes as she watches him at night. And finally in his own account of a giant air battle. Each of these instances is interesting because only one is objective: the photo. Yet it has been scratched out (my guess is he scratched it out). The other three are all manifestations of a perspective. Gina remembers him as a young and talented pilot. Fio sees him as a man sorting through cartridges. And Marco sees himself as a lost combat ace with no friends left alive. Out of all of these human faces, the photo seems to be someone (assuming Marco scratched himself) he does not want to be, Gina’s memory is from a blissful past, Fio’s perception is dark and perhaps sleepy, and Marco’s own memory is one of pain. I want to focus most on Fio’s perception, because it is the only one in the real present.</p>

<p>The reason why I think many reviewers’ focus on how Marco can break the pig curse is wrong, is because I think ultimatley Marco <em>does not want to be human</em>. The only time we see in present perspective Marco’s human face is when Fio sees him sorting through cartridges in a trance-state, bent on killing Curtis the next day in their air fight. When I saw this face it was not something touching or heartwarming, it was scary. This was not a good man, this was an evil man looking at bullets. And indeed, when Fio calls out to him, the person who responds is not human-marco, it is porco-marco: he responds with a laugh and a tender smile.</p>

<h3 id="flying">Flying</h3>
<p>Flying is the central movement of this plot, it drives the action, it provides the motivation, it takes up the scenery. Yet, I would not say that it is a propagandistic sort of flying. The Masks of War says that any fetishization of air machines is the air force’s way of tricking people into signing up. The air force is one thing only: it is man’s love of scientific achievement and machines. Clearly, the Top Gun films fit into this propaganda definition. Yet while the love of machines is clearly within the film, the feeling of propaganda is not. Perhaps it’s the ridiculousness of a pig flying. Marco himself says, “a pig’s gotta fly”. But also, I think it is because while films like Top Gun emphasize the exhilartion, the skill, the technicality, the achievement of flying, Porco Rosso mainly emphasizes the freedom of flying. Certainly, characters in both <em>love</em> to fly, but why they love to fly seems different.</p>

<p>///////
Points to talk about:</p>

<p>Marco as pig –&gt; he is more human when pig than when he is human. His human face appears only three times: once in a picutre, scratched out, once in battle, when all his friends have died and are going to heaven, and once when Fio sees him ultra-focused, sorting through bullets. His freedom is constantly under threat not only by bankruptcy, but by other jealous pilots, greedy pirates, the facisct government, and even love from and for Gino.</p>

<p>Men —&gt; the pirates want money and love, but seem to want each other more. and honor too. Curtis is a creep, but he doesn’t seem evil, although he gets carried away often; also Curtis is the classic swash buckling American white man, perhaps a joke on Americans?</p>

<p>Flying —&gt; flying is center in this film: everything is about it, the whole plot moves because of it. Is this a propaganda film, as the Masks of War suggests? Unlike all the Top Gun films, the machine itself, although important both visiually and plot wise, does not seem to be fetishized. Rather, the fragility and the murderousness of the machines is fully on display. Is flying a curse? Both a reminder of the evil it brings, but also the freedom and release it brings?</p>

<p>The ocean —&gt; why are most of theplanes seaplanes? I think this has to do with the idea of freedom. With wheels, you have to land on a strip. With sea boards, you can land anywhere. The government, the regulations, haven’t caught up with you yet.</p>

<p>Small time people —&gt; these people are everyhwere, from the mechanic and his family, to the bogus “federation” of pirates, to Gina, to Porco himself, and to all the various side unamed townsfolk characters, trying to survive in the post war, depression economy environment. They make things work… but do they really? The wager Fio makes of her body for money, perhaps that is a reference to the rampant prostitution of that time?</p>

<p>Time, era, place —&gt; clearly post WW1 Italy, this film takes place in the more sophisticated northern section of italy.</p>

<p>Women —&gt; from Gina to Fio, to the family of Piccolo, what role do they play? Fio is the classic ghbili young but strong and smart girl, trying to find her purpose in life. Gina is sophisticated wife left behind, though we see she is more than that, a hostess, a businessperson, a spy even? But at heart, I think she is someone waiting for her love to come home and stop playing dumb games in the air. A very touching line in the film: Picollo prays before lunch, asking for forgiveness that he must employ womens’ hands to rebuild Porco’s seaplane. 
Yet if Marco really stopped flying and joined Gina, would Gina be happy? One has to ask: why did Gina marry three out of the four guys (Marco’s friendgroup), and they were all pilots? She loves pilots. So isn’t what she wants a contradiction in itself? She loves the pilot, yet doesn’t want him to fly. Could it ever work out? Perhaps this would be the most clear example of Absence and Agony there is! The beloved, always moving, always somewhere else, the lover, always waiting, always still. (There’s also so many other Barthes sections here, such as the dual play between men talking about Fio and Gina, or Fio asking about Gina, and so on)</p>

<p>History —&gt; Unlike most of his other works, this film by miyazaki is clearly set historically. It is this setting which creates the shadow lurking behind everything, the evil that should inform our entire viewing of the movie. Facsim is on the rise, seen a few times in the film, and referenced obliquely through the depression. 
    We should also note the inevitable contrast of the beauty of the skies and the landscape with the horror of what must war have been like, even in the air with so called ‘gentleman’ pilots. Are the fights, hostage situations, robberies, and matches that Porco finds himself in but a pale joke reflection of the real horror that has taken place before, and will soon take place after? It turns out that after all, everything these people were doing was nothing in comparison with what the governments of these nations would do.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Better to be a pig than a fascist. Ironic, isn't it? Twisting the usual combination of words completley around. 
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>How does this relate to us? —&gt; I think this film is very relevant. The problem of economic downturn, lack of resources, crime waves, fascist government, rowdy populace, and streeghtfighting… what does one even do? Porco can fly away, but even he has to refuel, eat, and fix his aircraft. What can we do in a time of danger and imminent mass destruction? Nothing. If there’s one thing I don’t like about this film it’s the ending. It shows the pirates all happy at Gina’s hotel, and Fio happily narrating the last sequence. But we know this isnt true: The next war happens soon after, and everyone should be dead or at least gone.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First posted 2022-12-13]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Books Wrapped 2022</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/09/Books-Read-Wrapped.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Books Wrapped 2022" /><published>2022-12-09T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-09T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/09/Books-Read-Wrapped</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/09/Books-Read-Wrapped.html"><![CDATA[<p>First posted 2022-12-09</p>

<p>I have a big list of books read. However, this list for the majority of its exsistence was haphazard and not well curated. Its metadata elements were not thought out, and most of it used to be just a title of the book read. Slowly, the documentation got better, I started including the author, the year, the publishing, and so on. Finally, in 2022 Feb, I started doing systematic documentation, with title, year, edition, creator, editors/translators, publisher, and date that I finished reading the book. Although still not incomplete (because I did not include days spent reading, but that’s ok because I will just use the time between books as ‘days spent reading’), it is a much better system of documentation than the olden days where I just wrote “Odyssey”.</p>

<p>So in the style of Spotify Wrapped, Youtube Rewind, and others, I slowly input a CSV chart with this year’s read books. Then, using skills learned from LIS 572, taught by Melanie Walsh, I did some basic data science with R. Here are the results.</p>

<p>First, the dataset: <a href="/assets/BooksReadAllTimeDataset2022.csv">2022 Books Rewind Dataset CSV</a>
RStudio: <a href="/assets/2022booksrewind.R">2022 Books Rewind RStudio</a></p>

<p>Since the LCSH is very extensive and I didn’t want to spend even more time looking for the right fit, I split the ‘about’ metadata into two main column variables: genre <em>qua</em> subject, and genre <em>qua</em> form (type). This is for the viewers, because my own inside my head classification scheme may be a bit weird. In any case, I have included my own simplified mental genre scheme as well.</p>

<p>The number of pages read are gotten from each book’s total pages from google books. I tried to find the most accurate edition relative to mine. The page number is obviously not normalized for font size and spacing and book size. That would be impossible. They are simply a reflection of what the physical book says. It is likely that the total pages read should be lessened by 20%, given the fact that many of the books have indexes, title pages, and other miscellenia.</p>

<p>Pages per day is meant to simply be a general reflection of how fast I read that book.</p>

<h3 id="quick-facts">Quick Facts</h3>
<p>Time frame of Dataset: 2022 Feb 08 to 2022 Dec 09 <br />
Total days: 304 days</p>

<p>Total books read: 51 <br />
Total pages read: 17,949 <br />
Average pages read per day: 59 <br />
Average page count per book: 350</p>

<p>Shortest book: 124 pages<br />
Longest book: 1184 pages</p>

<p>First, let’s take a look at the number of books read per month. Figure 1:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/BRATbooksreadpermonth2022feb2022december.jpeg" alt="Books read per month" /></p>

<p>The next figure below shows the number of pages read per month. Figure 2:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/BRATpagesreadpermonth2022feb2022december.jpeg" alt="Pages read per month" /></p>

<p>From Figure 1 and 2 we can see some trends. Let me explain. <br />
In March, there is a big slowdown in reading. This is due to the fact that the war in Ukraine started in late Feburary, and I spent the majority of my time being anxiety ridden and following the war very closely. During that spring break I also spent a lot of time playing the newly released Elden Ring. A series of anxiety and distraction. <br />
In May the reading spikes greatly, I think due to the fact that I had mostly finished most of my projects early, due to a special event I had to attend, so I was just coasting. 
Reading is middling during the summer due to some other things I had to do which I didn’t want to do. But I was in a muddle and I was lying to myself and others. So being in such a muddle, as Old Man Emerson says to Lucy, one gets nothing done and wallows in self pity and lost time. Still, it wasn’t a totally abysmal amount of reading.<br />
September is when the reading drops again dramatically because I spent most of that month backpacking. It was great. 
October and November spike greatly because my classes for this semester were not only fun, but also lighter on work compared to previous classes. Taking those classes was highly enjoyable.</p>

<p>The third figure shows the number of books read per Genres-Subjects. Figure 3:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/BRATbooksreadpersubjectgenre2022feb2022dec.jpeg" alt="Books per genre subject" /></p>

<p>The fourth figure shows the number of books read per William’s internal simplified classification scheme. Figure 4:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/BRATwilliamgenres.jpeg" alt="William's internal classification" /></p>

<p>As you can see, the vast majority of books read have to do with ‘history’. And even some of the ‘skill’ books, and ‘what is to be done’ books, have their basis in history or deal with historical situations. For example, it can be said that Herman Khan’s “On Thermonuclear War” is as much a ‘skill’ book on the strategy and tactics of nuclear war, as it is a history on nuclear development and thought. But since it is different enough from most of the other history books, it is classified as a ‘skill’ book in my mental scheme.</p>

<p>You will also notice a bunch of comic books near the bottom of the dataset. This is due to the reccomendation of E, who showed me the world of Frank. From Frank, I then looked at the publisher and found Fantagraphic Books, a small, dedicated comic/graphic novel publishing company in Georgetown, South Seattle area. From that company I looked at other titles and started exploring the world of comic books, for lack of a better term.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First posted 2022-12-09]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interactive Open Letter to ABC Township Council on the Matter of Funding for ABC Public Library</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/05/Public-Library-Advocacy-Letter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interactive Open Letter to ABC Township Council on the Matter of Funding for ABC Public Library" /><published>2022-12-05T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-05T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/05/Public-Library-Advocacy-Letter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/05/Public-Library-Advocacy-Letter.html"><![CDATA[<p>The following letter is referenced from our <a href="/assets/PresentationLetterToABCTownshipCouncil.pdf">shorter presentation</a>.</p>

<p>An open letter to the ABC Township Council, from the ABC Public Library:</p>

<p>Dear Fellow Citizens,</p>

<p>The recent economic crisis has hit hard, and we understand and personally feel the pain that is being felt across our community. In the upcoming town budget review, we urge you, as leaders of the community, to strongly consider to continue to fund the public library. Not only will your vote in support of the library allow patrons to continue to enjoy library collections and services, but it will also allow the community to save a lot of money. Given that ABC Town is now suffering a severe deficit, we believe that is in the best financial interests of the community to have a fully functioning library. Although many beneficial aspects of a public library are difficult to quantify in monetary terms, we have attempted to present quantified data where possible, and contextualize them in the proper setting. We draw inspiration for the definition of subjective value from the general guidelines outlined in <a href="https://journals.uic.edu/ojs/index.php/fm/article/download/3765/3074">this paper on how to describe and measure library value from 2011</a>.</p>

<p>Although the public library may not seem like a place which generates revenue, it in fact holds a great return on investment for the community. The <a href="https://www.lrs.org/about/">Library Research Service</a>, a department within the Colorado State Library, estimates that public libraries throughout America have a return on investment of <a href="https://www.lrs.org/2020/02/19/how-much-is-your-library-worth/">up to four times</a> the money put in!</p>

<p>The direct monetary ROI sources of public libraries include:</p>
<ol>
  <li>A public library saves money for patrons by allowing them to borrow materials, for which they otherwise would have had to pay for.</li>
  <li>A public library saves money for patrons who otherwise would not have known how to find the material they were looking for, by enabling them to locate the material and use it.</li>
  <li>A public library saves time for patrons in finding material, time saved which can equate to money generated elsewhere.</li>
  <li>A public library uses local goods and services which circulates money back into the community.</li>
  <li>A public library encourages foot traffic, which stimulates patrons to visit and spend at nearby services and businesses.</li>
  <li>A public library compensates its librarians for their work, compensation which would not exsist without the library.</li>
</ol>

<p>In addition to monetary ROI, the public library also generates subjective value through educating the community:</p>
<ol>
  <li>A public library helps its patrons find materials they are looking for.</li>
  <li>A public library helps its patrons find materials that they may not even know they want.</li>
  <li>A public library helps its patrons navigate tricky government websites.</li>
  <li>A public library helps its patrons set up the basic foundations of start ups.</li>
</ol>

<p>And finally, the public library provides tremendous social value to the community:</p>
<ol>
  <li>A public library provides a community space for citizens to meet and talk to each other.</li>
  <li>A public library provides a safe space for young people and marginalized people to browse and find books that might inspire and speak to them.</li>
  <li>A public library provides a free, quiet, and comfortable space to relax, study, and work.</li>
  <li>A public library provides a fixed landmark in the community which gives the community pride and joy.</li>
</ol>

<p>Although educational and social benefits are difficult to measure quantitatively, they have the potential to indirectly create big monetary ROI. For example, if a marginalized young person, such as a gay student, is inspired by browsing in the stacks, or feels like a book speaks to them, that will be much <a href="https://www.ifla.org/files/assets/hq/topics/libraries-development/documents/how_libraries_provide_safe_spaces_to_all_youth.pdf">better for their mental health and self-image</a>, than if said student continued to feel isolated, and was denied information which represented who they are. To put it more bluntly, people with mental health problems are not effective producers in society, and require more government resources to help them resolve their issues. Of course, there is also the moral element to protecting and guiding the young people of our community.</p>

<p>Here is another example. By providing public rooms for community members to meet, public libraries foster the potential for innovation and new community groups to spring up. Simply by facilitating the free space, public libraries can encourage community contact and growth spontaneously. The more a people trust and know each other, the more likely they are going to visit each other’s businesses, create new start ups, help each other in time of need, and so on. In this sense, the public library acts as a hub and also as a helper for citizens who wish to use library resources to eudcate themselves and to take the first steps in their new business. As the <a href="https://www.ala.org/advocacy/sites/ala.org.advocacy/files/content/Workforce/LBB_Playbook_web_013122.pdf">American Library Association’s “Libraries Build Business playbook”</a> states: half of all public libraries in the US are already providing some sort of business related help (whether this be printing, government permit finding, or vocational degree education) to small businesses, and their beneficial economic impact is easily felt by beginning entrepreneurs who lack the immediate capital funding.</p>

<p>Concretley, research shows that across America, the ROI of public libraries is <a href="https://www.lrs.org/data-tools/public-libraries/return-on-investment/recent-studies/">consistently much higher than 1</a>:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/586libraryROI1.jpeg" alt="ROI across major US states" /></p>

<p>Therefore, instead of privatizing public libraries, as a certain Forbes article suggests, or decreasing funding overall, we urge the township council and the community to further support ABC Public Library with public tax money, in order to guarantee public services and foster a stronger and more resilient community. <a href="https://berryvillelibrary.org/the-value-of-public-libraries/">A library that is public at core is beholden to the community, and not to private corporate interests</a>. A public library exsists to provide services, to educate, and to look out for the community. Even when the public library is physically closed, our online services can still help people browse, hold books in advance, find government resources, and stay up to date with local events.</p>

<p>Thank you for your time and attention, we appreciate your dedication and support and hope to hear from you in the future!</p>

<p>Sincerely, <br />
The ABC Public Library</p>

<p>Below are more resources demonstrating the immense value of public libraries:<br />
<a href="https://www.ala.org/tools/research/librariesmatter/category/general-economic-impact">American Library Association Studies Library ROI in three catagories: Economic, Educational, Social</a><br />
<a href="https://www.lrs.org/fast-facts-reports/colorado-libraries-return-on-investment-5-to-1/">Colorado Libraries Return on Investment Study reveals 5 ROI.</a><br />
<a href="https://www.lrs.org/data-tools/public-libraries/return-on-investment/">Colorado Libraries ROI Case Study Sources.</a>
<a href="https://berryvillelibrary.org/the-value-of-public-libraries/">A Short Summary on the Value of Public Libraries</a> <br />
<a href="https://www.lrs.org/documents/closer_look/roi.pdf">Public Libraries, A Wise Investment (2009) PDF</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The following letter is referenced from our shorter presentation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LIS 572 Oregon Logs Data Project</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/04/Oregon-Logs-Data-Project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LIS 572 Oregon Logs Data Project" /><published>2022-12-04T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2022-12-04T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/04/Oregon-Logs-Data-Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2022/12/04/Oregon-Logs-Data-Project.html"><![CDATA[<p>LIS 572: Data Science with Professor Melanie Walsh. <br />
By William Wu and Ben Hauptman. <br />
First published: 2022-12-04. <br />
Updated with weighted values: 2022-12-05.</p>

<h3 id="introduction">Introduction</h3>
<p>The question we looked into was if macroeconomic swings could be detected through the price of logs. We used a dataset provided by the Oregon Department of Forestry. We chose this dataset because Oregon is a large supplier of logs throughout the Northwest.</p>

<p><em>(Note, Pond Value refers to the price paid for an unprocessed log at a processing plant. Where the logs are stacked are called “Ponds”. Log price and pond value are the same).</em></p>

<p>Since we knew that Douglas Fir is very common in Oregon, and since we also knew that Douglas Fir is comomnly used in building construction, we <em>predicted that data analysis on this dataset would indeed produce results that clearly show the economic crisis of 2008</em>.</p>

<p>The dataset can be found here: <a href="https://data.oregon.gov/Natural-Resources/Log-Prices/4v4m-wr5p">Oregon Log Prices Dataset</a>.<br />
Our code can be found here: <a href="/assets/WEIGHTEDOregonLogPricesRASSETSv2.R">Oregon Log Prices R Analysis</a>.</p>

<h4 id="context-concerning-the-dataset-from-the-oregon-department-of-forestry">Context Concerning the Dataset from the Oregon Department of Forestry</h4>
<p>The dataset that we decided to use was from the Oregon Department of Forestry. The raw dataset has 7,884 distinct rows of data about sold logs over the course of 15 years, from 2000 to 2015. It also contains some data from 2016, but because the data is incomplete for that year we decided against using it as part of our analysis and final dataset. (We will talk more about our computational process below). The raw dataset has seven different variables tracked for each column, with those variables being:</p>
<ol>
  <li>The <strong>Year</strong> it was sold</li>
  <li>The <strong>Quarter</strong> it was sold in that year</li>
  <li>what <strong>Region</strong> the log came from</li>
  <li>The <strong>Species</strong> of log</li>
  <li>The <strong>Grade</strong> it was given</li>
  <li>The price it was sold for (“<strong>Pond Value</strong>”), and</li>
  <li>The number of people who bid on the log / the number of pond centers called. (“<strong>Quote</strong>”).</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="ethical-concerns">Ethical Concerns</h4>
<p>There does not seem to be any glaring ethical concerns, mostly because none of the pond processing plants are identified by name, nor are any specific geo-located logging coordinates expressed anywhere in the dataset or on the government website.</p>

<p>Apart from the dataset itself, there may be environmental ethical concerns over logging, and whether or not this dataset and our analysis may encourage further exploitation and destruction of Oregon’s forests, which is <a href="https://www.oregonwild.org/about/press/report-oregon-lost-500000-acres-deforestation-2000">depleting at an alarming rate</a>.</p>

<h4 id="some-issues-with-column-variables">Some Issues with Column Variables</h4>
<p>The main issue with the data is that we have been unable to get in contact with the data collector/creator/curator (Julie from the Oregon Department of Forestry). Without her help, we are unable to use one of the column variables at all (Grade), and we are not 100% certain of the meaning of one of two of the column variables (Quotes, Year).</p>

<p>First, let it be known that Grade <em>refers to both the size/shape and quality/purpose of the logs</em>. As you can probably tell, with four sub-variables exsisting in one column variable, it becomes very difficult to make any interpretations, especially when they are often intermingled. For example, some rows were labled just 2P (quality and use of wood), others were labled just 8”-14” (size), and some were labled with both 3S (12”+). We think that there is likely some overlap in grading, which means that we cannot effectively use this variable. Luckily, we did not need to use Grade in our analysis to be able to help answer our question. For those who are interested in seeing how <em>grades</em> as a whole is calculated in Oregon, here is a <a href="https://www.oregon.gov/ODF/Documents/WorkingForests/LogTermDefinitions.pdf">quick government guide</a>.</p>

<p>Second, we are unsure of what the column variable Number of Quotes means exactly. It could be the number of quotes taken per quarter fat that listed price from different processing centers, or it could be the number of logs sold at that price quoted from various pond centers. Without this exact information, we would not know if quotes would indicate a weighting system. If the former, then each row would be weighted as 1. If the latter, then each row would be weighted according to the number of quotes listed.  Also, even if the value did indicate weight, we would not know <em>by how much</em>, because a quote from any pond center could indicate any number of logs. This is because unique pond centers <em>are not</em> listed as a column variable. <strong>Ultimatley, we decided to use the Quotes values as weights in themselves</strong>. Because not using quotes produces a drastically undervalued dataframe, using them should produce something closer to reality. However, it still highly likely the case that <em>total prices in our graphs are greatly under the reality</em>.</p>

<p>A final problem was the issue of Year. Does Year mean fiscal year? Or is it simply just calendar year? This problem did not really impact most of the dataset, except for the crucial years around 2007-2009. If Year means Fiscal Year, then Pond Values would not be predictive of the Great Recession. If Year means calendar year, then it could be argued that pond values may have the power to predict housing market crashes! This is because the meaning of Year would change the position of Quarter 4, which could be either seen as a predictive element or a lagging element in relation to the Great Recession. (US fiscal year starts with Quarter 1 in October).<br />
Given the absence of information, we have taken Year to mean Fiscal Year, as Quarter (1, 2, 3, 4) is usually used in a fiscal sense. This assumption seems to correlate with exsisting government information on home sales’ prices. (<a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/b/b8/Median_and_Average_Sales_Prices_of_New_Homes_Sold_in_United_States_1963-2016_annual.svg/1920px-Median_and_Average_Sales_Prices_of_New_Homes_Sold_in_United_States_1963-2016_annual.svg.png">Sales prices of new homes in the US</a>).</p>

<h4 id="computational-method-and-analysis">Computational Method and Analysis</h4>
<p>The raw dataset contains 7,884 distinct rows of information. Although already in quite good shape, we decided to further clean the data for a few reasons.</p>

<p>The very first thing we did was to remove three rows with N/A for prices. Pond value is the most important variable in our study, so rows without them were removed.</p>

<p>Next, we noticed that the data collection for 2016 was incomplete: that final year was missing quarters 3 and 4. Doing a quick group_by and count, we were able to see the distribution of the number of rows per year. As expected, 2016 had an abnormally low number of rows. We therefore completley deleted any rows which contained the year 2016. This left us with a remainder of 7,623 rows of information.</p>

<p>Dataset rows per year
<img src="/assets/RowCountByYear.jpg" alt="screenshot rows per year" /></p>

<p>One other issue we noticed was that the number of rows was slowly ramping up from 2000-2006, and then stabailized after 2007. Is the ramping up indicitive of a larger macro logging industry trend, or is it reflective of the building up of logging industry contacts as this dataset first started (and therefore indicating a lack of information in the first years of data collection)? Without a response from Julie, we do not know.</p>

<p>On a more specific level, while doing analysis on regions, we noticed that two regions only had a frequency of 1. These two rows were “6 - Klamath Unit” and “7 - Klamath Unit”. However, Klamath Unit already exsists as region 5. So we decided to slice those two out. Further along in our analysis on regions, we noticed that two regions were the exact same, but for some reason were split into two rows. We merged those two rows into one. (“2 &amp; 3 - Coos, Douglas Counties &amp; Roseburg”).</p>

<p>Region Count Raw
<img src="/assets/RegionCountRaw.jpeg" alt="Region Count Raw" /></p>

<p>Finally, the major issue we encountered was fixing the weight problem to the best of our ability. Because the standalone prices for each row are not weighted, we had to calculate weights for them using the Quotes column. First, we used as.numeric and regmatches to strip the column of anything that was not a numeric value, which left us with only numbers. Then we added the numbers to a new column in the same dataframe, calling it ‘weight’. Finally, we multipled ‘weight’ by ‘Pond.Value’, to get the ‘total_weight’. This gave us a much more accurate picture of the total amount of prices floating around as opposed to our earlier on when we did our entire analysis based off of <em>just</em> single pond values.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/WEIGHTEDpondvaluedataframescreenshot.jpeg" alt="weighted dataframe screenshot" /></p>

<p>For our analysis of the three main relationships, our most common code pattern was to group_by and then summarize(sum()) the cleaned dataset.</p>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-css" data-lang="css"><span class="nt">yearly_price_total</span> <span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="nt">-</span> 
  <span class="nt">log_prices_clean_2</span> <span class="o">%&gt;%</span> 
  <span class="nt">group_by</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nt">Year</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">%&gt;%</span> 
  <span class="nt">summarize</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nt">Pond</span><span class="nc">.Value</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="nt">sum</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nt">Pond</span><span class="nc">.Value</span><span class="o">))</span></code></pre></figure>

<p>This worked well for the relationships we were looking at:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Total Pond Value over Years</li>
  <li>Quartlery Pond Values over Years</li>
  <li>Pond Value by Species <br />
(Note that the Pond Value in each relationship refers to the aggregate Pond Value for each row in the targeted group_by variable).</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="analysis">Analysis</h3>
<p>The main insight from our analysis is that economic trends have a huge impact on log prices, and this impact is reflected clearly in the data. Perhaps it can even be said that the log prices may predict economic trends, as we see pond values fall even in 2007, before the Great Recession really kicks down the door. Looking at Figure 1, we can clearly see rising pond values from 2002-2007, and the subsequent nosedive in value during the Great Recession which started in December of 2007. Pond values dropped more than 30% in the span of just 2007-2009. The price nadir of 2009 was lower than anything else we had data on.</p>

<p>We can also see the tail end of the drop in prices of the decade long Dotcom Bubble. Comparatively speaking, the fall in prices at the end of the Dotcom Bubble in 2000-2002 was much more gentle than the extremely steep fall in prices during the Great Recession.</p>

<p>Note also the great increase in prices after 2009, which reflects the massive printing of money by the Federal Reserve and the reluctance by Obama and Yellen to reduce the interest rate. Although these actions may have helped grow the economy, it has only helped to create another bubble, one which are now facing right now. Furthermore, the incredibly rapid growth and rampant printing of money has allowed get rich schemes and companies to pop up left and right, and has greatly increased uncontrolled consumerist demand among the people. For example, note all the collapsed schemes in the crypto world (FTX), or in scilicon valley (Theranos), the effects and conseqeuences of which we are just starting to see unfold in the courts todays.</p>

<p>Thus, despite the above mentioned problem of lacking a <strong>true</strong> weighted variable to calculate actual number of logs, we were still able to see a very clear trend. We suspect that this is because the Oregon Department of Forestry likely has a policy in place which mandates some sort of equal selection of tree grade cutting, so that no one tree growth is cut in toto.</p>

<p>Figure 1:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/WEIGHTEDpricetoyear.jpeg" alt="yearly pond value aggregate" /></p>

<p>Next, in Figure 2, we can see that the quarterly values are not the most equal. Although in the past logging was highly seasonal, not only because people had nothing to do in the winter, but also because winter was when the ground was hard enough to drag logs, modern logging has become so effective that it can operate in any season. Furthermore, because of modern transportation, modern logging does not have to take place along rivers (which is why most major cities are located along big rivers: that’s where they can best accumulate wood.)</p>

<p>Therefore, we cannot draw any concrete conclusions from the small variations in quarterly price. Furthermore, we cannot draw conclusions because we do not have a true weight variable (as mentioned before, “Quotes” is not a true weight variable). (For more information on humanity’s interaction with trees, one should look into <a href="https://press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/D/bo79171450.html">Deforesting the Earth</a> by Michael Williams).</p>

<p>Figure 2:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/WEIGHTEDquarterlypondvalueOverYearsV3.jpeg" alt="quarters pond values over years" /></p>

<p>Continuing on to Figure 3, we can see why Oregon’s official state tree is the Douglas Fir. Out of the $20,953,065 grand total pond value in our calculation, the Douglas Fir holds the Douglas Fir holds 38.72% of sales! (At $8,113,795). The dataset clearly reflects the natural prevalence of the Douglas Fir in Oregon, but also displays its importance to the local rural logging economy and to the wider construction/real estate business.</p>

<p>Figure 3:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/WEIGHTEDspeicestopondvalue.jpeg" alt="species to pond value" /></p>

<p>Even when we zoom into looking at the price of Douglas Fir over time we can see the same economic turns reflected.</p>

<p>Figure 4:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/WEIGHTEDdouglasFirOnlyV3.jpeg" alt="Douglas Fir ONLY Pond Value over years" /></p>

<p>Finally, after normalizing both Total Yearly Pond Value and Total Yearly Douglas Fir Pond Value, we see that the scale of change is very similar. (The normalizing process we used was to divide each year’s price by the average of all the years).</p>

<p>Figure 5:</p>

<p><img src="/assets/WEIGHTEDoverlayV3.jpeg" alt="Overlay without legend, I couldn't get it to work" /></p>

<p>We assess that the extra increase in price of Douglas Fir at the apex of the housing bubble and the extra decrease in price at the nadir of the housing bubble are due to the fact that Douglas Fir is an indispensable and mass-logged species. Thus, during peak construction demand, you can never have enough, whereas when the housing boom ended, you will always have too much. Otherwise, the difference in the changes in price between Douglas Fir and the Aggregate Species’ Totals is not so drastic as to warrant further investigation.</p>

<h3 id="reflections">Reflections</h3>
<p>One possible direction this data could go would be to expand the current dataset to gain a much longer view of the ups and downs of log market prices. This could go both into the future and into the past, but work would have to be done to adjust prices relative to the current year’s level of inflation. It would also be interesting to compare the data against other states’ logging information, Federal logging information, and the logging information of other countries.</p>

<p>Finally, we just want to reiterate that the major problem we encountered was the lack of a proper weighting variable, due to the fact that we could not confirm what “Quotes” actually meant. It is highly likely “Quotes” is not truly representative as a weighting variable, due to the fact that one quote value <em>does not indiciate how many logs are included in that one quote</em>. However, having a number of quotes is better than no weight variable at all.</p>

<p>If Julie ever responds to us, it would be very interesting to see if the graphs change, depending on if we can obtain better weighting data. It is possible that we got very lucky with our current graphs, as they match our predictions and reflect historical ecnomic swings. However, in the future, it would be best to fully ascertain the meaning and weighting of all variables.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[LIS 572: Data Science with Professor Melanie Walsh. By William Wu and Ben Hauptman. First published: 2022-12-04. Updated with weighted values: 2022-12-05.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on Otto Von Bismarck</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/24/Otto-Von-Bismarck-Reflections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Otto Von Bismarck" /><published>2022-11-24T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-24T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/24/Otto-Von-Bismarck-Reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/24/Otto-Von-Bismarck-Reflections.html"><![CDATA[<p>First written: 2020 July 4-30.</p>

<p>This essay is based off multiple books about Bismarck, which I read in the summer of 2020.</p>

<h3 id="part-i">Part I</h3>
<h3 id="thoughts-on-otto-von-bismarck">Thoughts on Otto von Bismarck.</h3>

<p>Central question: can we blame Bismarck for WW1 and WW2?</p>

<p>The first thing we have to ask before we answer this question is what would have happened if Bismarck never was. (IE, we assume an alternate history after 1848. I choose 1848 because Bismarck does not have a high position yet, and this is the year of the Revolutions across Europe that fail).</p>

<p>Would the German states have unified regardeless? Would Austria have still maintained its empire? Would the other states, especially France and Russia, have acted differently? From what I have read (and I am by no means super familiar with 1815-1890), I am not sure if a total unified Germany would have at all appeared. It is likely that a Unified Germany consisting ONLY of the Northern German states would have arisen, due to numerous factors. As for the Southern German states, I am not sure. Especially given that Austria even at 1815, at the height of its political prestiege (with Metternich’s conducting of the peace of Vienna, and the creation of the “Concert of Europe) was in economic shambles.</p>

<p>However, this much is clear: the North Germans, including all the way from East Prussia to the Rhineland, had a clear connection. Religiously, they were Lutheran, and economically, despite the vast difference between Prussian peasant based economies and Rhineish industrial revolution, they traded with each other a lot more than they did with Austria. Why? For many reasons.</p>

<p>First off, after the explosion of trade over the Atlantic (due to the rise of America), The German states had suffered a big stagnation in international trade in the 1700s. Because of this stagnation, they started to trade more with each other. Austria, however, was not as impacted, because of its geographic nearness to the East (IE Russia), its geographic isolation from the rest of the German Confederation [Austria is interesting in that it’s borders from the rest of the German Confederation are dotted with numerous high mountain peaks, these being essentially the eastern tail of the Swiss alps], and because of its own internal market: the various ethnicities and imperial lands of the Austrian Empire.</p>

<p>[The Southern German states, then, are the interesting ones, since they were both close to Austria and close to the North German states. In reality, however, the South German states tended to not want to get involved, being firecly proud of their own independence in all matters, to the detriment of cooperation even amongst themselves (these states being Baden, Wuttemberg, Bavaria). Furthremore, the South German states generally like to cooperate with France, France being a Catholic country, and because of their more-than-friendly relations during the Napoleonic era, where the Southern states benefited while being client states of the French Empire.]</p>

<p>Back to the hypothetical:<br />
It is possible that if Bismarck did not appear, Northern Germany might have unified into some sort of entity. Most likely this entity would have taken an economic form, due to the fact that North Germany’s network of natural rivers and man-made canals provide a very convienent North-South AND East-West transport system. However, even this scenario of mine runs into trouble.</p>

<p>Why? Because, as is shown in the ACTUAL history of Germany, the various states of North AND South Germany all highly value their independence, and generally speaking voted liberally against the Conservative Monarchic impulses of Prussia. Especially after the year 1848, the various monarchies of Europe, especially those of Austria and Prussia, had to institute various Constitutional Guarantees and other reforms. Thus, would Prussia have allowed North-German unification at the exepense of its own monarchy and conservative values? Furthermore, would Austria have allowed it? It is important to remember that despite its rotten interior political, social, and economic situation, Austria still possessed the facade of a Great Power and still had a sizeable army (even if it was pretty bad for a Great Power). Thus, it is very difficult to assess what William I, his cabinet, and the parliament would have done if Bismarck never exsisted. Most likely, even if William I allowed for calls for a parliamentary North German bloc, Austria would have found some way to stop it, either by direct intervention or calling in French or British aid. Thus, if Bismarck never exsisted, it might be the case that the German states continued on in their little confusing-border-lines fashion, even to this day. It was Bismarcks will and cunning that created unified Germany.</p>

<p>As one good video on youtube put it: Europe was delicate balance of powers, and at its center, were a bunch of German states in a balance of powers. (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ME_tV4849NQ)</p>

<p>BISMARCK AS A PERSON: <br />
It is difficult to discern what Bismarck really wanted in his position as leader of Germany for 30+ years. At first it seemed like he simply wanted a return to conservative enlightened absolutism. But it is clear in his various writings that he did not like total absolutism. Nor did he like parliamentarism. In fact, after reading all about him, I get the feeling that he just wanted to rule everything himself, and have everyone agree with him. Bismarck was probably the closest anyone in the modern era got to being King without actually being King.</p>

<p>Bismarck, despite his temper and his crazy and intense speeches, was not actually a physically violent man. He often cried, made pleas to the King William I, multiple times threatened to resign in a rain of tears and an outburst of anger, and one time even threatened to jump out of a window, all because the King and the ministers wouldn’t do what he said. Furthermore, despite his contemporary image of “Iron and Blood”, in reality, he was a man who was deeply civilian in nature. Having only served in the reserves for one year, his image in his later years of a man always in military uniform covers the fact that he ALWAYS had other options ready before he resorted to force. In fact, in his Iron and Blood speech he didn’t actually threaten the use of force, but rather, that the use of force was one of the possibilities he was prepared for in order to get what he wanted.</p>

<p>But what did Bismarck really want? I am inclined to think that at the very beginning, he wanted to quell the Liberals and put an end to the constitutional deadlock, where the liberal majority would not approve an extension of the military bill, and the King and his ministers kept pushing for the bill. Ultimatley, after 4+ years of deadlock, what solved the issue was not an internal agreement, but rather, Bismarck’s eventual use of German Nationalism against Austrian arrogance to solidify his and William I’s prestiege: the fact that Austria would not cede in any matters relating to Prussian control North of the Main river provided a nice pretext for the buildup of greivances and hostilities between Prussia and Austria. German nationalism only soared even more when Prussia and Austria “half annexed” Schewlsig-Holstein from Denmark. And later when Austria refused to give Prussia full control (despite Austria having literally no land border with the peninsula), a quick victory over them by the Prussian military only caused nationalism to soar even higher.</p>

<p>Bismarck was thus correct when he realized that Nationalism need not be a Liberal idea.</p>

<h4 id="important-note">IMPORTANT NOTE:</h4>
<p>(We take Nationalism as inherently tied to Conservatism. This was not the case. Nationalism in the olden days was opposed to monarchism. IE, one is rule by people nationale, the other is rule by King with divine right. We might credit Bismarck with tearing Nationalism away from Liberalism and tying it to Conservatism).</p>

<p>Thus, through this war, Bismarck managed to tear one pillar of the Liberal majority out from under them: especially since he used unconstitutional means to achieve German nationalism (IE, he funded the military without budget approval, and he mobilized without approval as well). Thus, already we can see some strains concerning the fact that Bismarck was very apt to use un-constitutional means to achieve his objectives. From the start, he stifled anti-conservative newspapers, he jailed people with prison sentences (usually 6 months) to stop them from attacking the King, he continued military spending without the military bill actually being ratified, and he mobilized the Prussian army without consent of the Parliament. HOWEVER. It must be noted that these were his MEANS, not his ENDS. Again, the question becomes, whad did Bismarck really wasnt? What were his ends?</p>

<p>After Prussia crushing victory over Austria in 1866, Bismarck did something almost no other statesman would have done: he left the defeated opponent, Austria, alone. He took not a single inch of Austrian soil. Against the inclinations of the entire cabinet, the military staff, and King William I, Bismarck forced his will through and stopped the follow-through invasion of Austria that was planned so eagerly by the High Command. Why did he do this? Because in reality, the foreign war with Austria was not so much a move in international politics, but rather a timely and convienent way to CEMENT CONSERVATIVE MONARCHIC, AND PRUSSIAN POWER BACK IN NORTHERN GERMANY. Thus, in reality, he was not fighting to destroy Austria, but 1. to force Austria to recognize Prussia’s supremacy north of the Main River, and 2. to foster German Nationalist sentiment at home, thus leading to the crumbling of the Liberal majority in Parliament.</p>

<p>But how did Bismarck manage to do this? In fact, it was only because of Bismarck’s incredible skill at playing one side off another side that he managed to pull this off. This is one example of his GENIUS level statesmanship and political/diplomatic intrigue. In any other timeline of history without a Bismarck, most likely France would have interevened in the conflict to prevent Prussia from attacking Austria. But Bismarck avoided this (and other eventualities) by doing what he did best: he took the position of the pivot, he took the fulcrum. He prevented France’s entry into the Prussian Austrian War by playing on Napoleon III’s fear of an Prussian-Austrian reconciliation, while he tried to squeeze as many concessions out of Vienna as possible by playing on Franz Josef’s fear of a Prussian-Franco alliance. Only until the fact that Austria got tired of conceding to Prussia, and had actually mobilized its army, did Bismarck slowly head towards the use of the Prussian army, but even then, he conducted secret negotiations with Vienna in order to avert war.</p>

<p>Bismarck’s inclination to only make the vital decision at the very last possible moment is a reoccuring theme in his life. It was not because he was afraid of making the decision, but rather, that he wanted to be sure that it was the “most useful decision with the least harm possible” that he could make. Furthermore, especially in the case of war, Bismarck did not like to make decision until the last moment because war “can never be controlled”, whereas political intrigue and fear-mongering CAN be controlled and manipulated (however, this is to finally prove wrong when he meets the stubborness of William II).</p>

<p>After the Seven Weeks war and the consequent unification of North Germany into the North German Confederation, Bismarck quickly switched tacts. Instead of being a staunch Prussian conservative, he became a German Nationalist, and started proposing liberal ideas, such as welfare. This is extremely important because it shows that Bismarck doesn’t really care about any principle, except the principle of the aggrandizement of the state. Once Prussia had accomplished its role as the unifier of North Germany, Bismarck instantly turns his focus to North Germany as whole, instead of only particularly focusing on the prestiege and power of Prussia.</p>

<p>One could also say that the only thing he cares about is power, which is also true. His own power, to say the least.</p>

<p>I notice that this is getting a bit long, so I’m going to shorten the rest of the history post 1866-1890 up a bit. Basically, some machinations induce a war between France and Prussia, and Prussia goes to war with France, but this time, Bismarck can’t stop the Generals from fully invading france, so now he is stuck in a year long siege of Paris, because the French aren’t giving up. So contrary to the claim that the war with France was used to unify the Southern German states, in fact, it was the unification of the Southern German states with the North Confederation that allowed for the prolongation and prosecution of the war with France. LOL. But in any case, the war shows that the South German states had to choose a side: and they chose North Germany instead of France or Austria.</p>

<p>In any case: after that, Bismarck basically settled into a position of not wanting to risk the new Germany. He didn’t want anymore wars, or anymore entanglements. He saw that he had unified and conquered as much as he could morally defend, (basically he unified German lands, with the exception of Metz, which he added in a fit of anger in the treaty with Paris after the Franco-Prussian war, an addition that was to cause him and Germany much pain later).</p>

<p>However, his very inflamation of German nationalism would haunt germany later: for the new generation of Germans, including William II, wanted prestiege, they wanted global empire, they wanted economic prosperity, they wanted a navy big enough to rival England’s. Instead of the pursuit of the possible, instead of reasons of state, these new leaders had reasons of principle: Power, Glory, Wealth: most importantly (and most disastoursly), all to be achieved outside of exsisting German lands. Thus, Bismarck’s unification of the Reich inadventendly gave William II and his military advisors the tool needed to exert German Domination.</p>

<p>LET US RECAP: Bismarck did everything FOR THE STATE. He was not interested in principles. His goals were these as follows, and in this historical order. The preservation of Prussian military power and monarchy. The establishement of Prussian supremacy in North Germany and the creation of the North German Confederation. The Preservation of the confederation. Then the semi-unwanted war with France and the subsequent Formation of the German Reich (in fact the second one in Germany’s millenia long history). The preservation of the German Reich.</p>

<p>So was Bismarck just a unprincipled crazy man? Power hungry? Everything for the State? Perhaps. But what one forgets is that even the state itself, or power, is a principle. Although people praise Bismarck for being innovative and a practitioner of real politik (or accuse him of it): isn’t this what european monarchs have been doing for centuries? All of them, despite being kings, fight and kill each other, all for power, land, glory. The whole reason I still don’t clearly understand the 1800s is simply because the whole mess of alliances and possible alliances and blocs of alliances and this and that is just so confusing and makes no sense. Why does it make no sense? Because all of these alliances are based on expediencies and power, not only any true principle like democracy, like we western countries practise today (although even the “demoracy principle” is shaky and questionable if we are to look at the actions of some “democratic” countries). This is why reading about Bismarck is so confusing. At any time in the historical narrative, he has multiple motives, multiple methods, multiple endgame scenarios planned out. And to a lesser extent, all the other countries do the same. You never know completely what’s going on.</p>

<p>In reality, Bismarck didn’t do anything new, he just took it to the next level. Instead of letting any sort of sentiment cloud him or block his judgement, like the lust for conquest and glory that plagued the German generals from the Seven Weeks War to Operation Barbarossa, Bismarck knew how to wait, he knew how to manipulate, he knew when to start, and MOST IMPORTANTLY, HE KNEW WHEN TO STOP. Bismarck upheld the PRINCIPLE OF POWER to its purist and utmost form, with no blemishes. It was his perogative to do anything to aggrandize the state as much as possible, and preserve it, without risking German lives. In this sense, Bismarck was one of the greatest statesman in all time. Under no other leader has a country grown so fast in land and economic power, and done so relatively bloodlessly.</p>

<p>(In my opinion, Hitler could have very well stopped after taking over Czeoslovakia, but he decided to take one step further and conquer Poland. If he had stopped after taking over the Bohemian lands, he would have very well once more formed a New German Reich equal, if not greater, in prestiege, power, and prosperity to Bismarck’s Reich.)</p>

<p>So can we blame Bismarck for what happened after he died? The popular metaphore is that Bismarck created a state that resembeled a souped-up-race car, one that only he knew how to drive without crashing. But this is unfair. Why should we blame him for the creation of a car like this? Couldn’t the next driver of the car driven slowly? (Or, are we to blame the gun on the table for the murder of an innocent?) The counterargument would be then: well if you put a fast car in a excitable man’s hands like those of William II’s, there is bound to be a high-speed accident. (Or, if you give the police a hammer they will see every problem as a nail.) Still then the counterargument to that would be: well, why not blame other nations, like Russia or Austria, both of which are monarchies and both of which also have large resources at their disposal?</p>

<p>Ultimatley, however, it is perhaps true that the VERY formation of Bismarck’s German Reich allowed for the conditions of WWI. Otherwise, what reasons would Russia and France have for fighting again? Like the fun youtube video I linked said: Europe was a delicate balance of powers, and at its center, was delicate a balance of powers. It is precisely because Prussia rose to become the Great Power of Germany that completley altered this delicate balance of powers. In this sense, YES, we can indeed blame Bismarck for the consequent WW1, and maybe even WW2. But this is an unfair placement of blame. If that is the case, we could also blame the Meiji Restoration for the Pacific war, a restoration that was in fact one of democratic values, openess, western economic advacement, and western social norms! Or we can blame the British for trying to maintain their empire and not allowing Germany to try and get some. And so on.</p>

<p>In fact, Pre Facist Japan in the 1920s heavily resemebled that of Weimar Germany, if not more so, in its freedom of speech and tolerance of new ideas. It was only because of the military’s resentment at being sidelined, that led to their coup d’etat over the democratic establishement in Japan. And much like in Germany, none of the democratic Japanese statesment thought to control the military establishement.
(We might also then blame Einstein for the Cold War!)</p>

<p>Similary, this is what happened in Germany. Although Bismarck thought of the army only as a tool to his State ends, Bismarck failed to take into account the long lasting effects of raising the army to such a prestigious and powerful role in German society. He also failed to see that the army leaders would have thoughts and values of their own, quite distinct from Parliamentary Germany. This is what would throw William II into war, and what would consequently choke the development of Weimar Democracy for its entire 20 year lifespan, due to the fact that no matter what, the spectre of the Army loomed behind the Weimar Parliament, ready for any excuse of revolutionary activity to pounce.</p>

<p>Thus, I would say that it is not so much the unification of Germany that was the issue, but rather the lasting implications that Bismarck left behind during his unification of Germany. Like I said, he used the army to coerce, he silenced enemy papers, he locked people up with (admittedly) light jail times for opposition, he decieved and promised people on both sides at the same time, he wrote the German constitution mostly by himself and left many loopholes in its conduct, thus allowing for a single man to take the position of fulcrum, independent of Judicial, Parliament, and Monarchic branches.</p>

<p>Furthermore, we must not forget that Germany’s political, national, and economic-industrial development all occured in the quick span of 1815-1900, whereas England, France, Russia, Austria, all had hundreds of years to consolidate their lands, develop their political institutions, and then move forward to industrial revolution. For Germany, all this happened in less than 100 years. So in fact, now that I have said all this, perhaps Bismarck IS to blame. Indeed, no one could have been so astute and delicate as he in the dangerous game of international and domestic politics. But was there a need for someone as astute as him? (Just like a trust that is given to a heir, the only thing the heir needs to do is not waste the money away, and it will slowly grow and become self-sufficient.) But perhaps the race car analogy is correct. Bismarck, the 6 foot tall fat man, was the only ballerina delicate enough to dance the line between so many conflicting powers and interests. It was obvious that William II had neither the patience nor the insight to do what Bismarck did.</p>

<p>But if we are to indeed blame Bismarck for WWI, then can we not blame the founding fathers for the rise of the Confederacy, and till even today, for White nationalism and Trump? If we are to blame the founders of a system or nation, then the Founding Fathers of this country are equally guilty, for not seeing how truly and deeply stupid and uneducated the masses really are, despite already taking that into account for the creation of our American democratic system.</p>

<p>For better or for worse, the modern nation has to be one of the NATIONAL premise, in order to effectively compete and prosper in this international world. Bismarck saw that in the 1850s, and he knew he had to act in order to preserve Prussia, and consequently, Germany’s independence, security, and propserity. In fact, he willingly made Germany off of the core of Prussia, instead of vice versa, and later emphasized GERMAN unity over Prussian power. The fact that subsequent statesmen were completely idiotic and inadequate cannot be blamed on him, for he tried his best to create a starting ground for the German Empire which would be prosperous and powerful. Perhaps the New German Empire wanted too much, things that were impossible. But this then goes into the reasons for WWI. And there are many reasons for WWI, not just on Germany’s side. But that is an entirely separate spiel that I can write if you want me to.</p>

<p>One can only imagine what would have happened if Germany remained a bunch of small ass states. Most likely, there would have been no WWI. Russia would still be a Tsarist country today, and Austria would still be a giant empire. The Ottoman empire would probably have disintegrated naturally, as it was on the path to doing so, and Greece would have formed as an independent Nation. . The UK would still maintain most of its colonies, and Germany would still be a relative backwater in Europe. The United States would remain in isolation, ever wary of European motives and extravagence. Essentially, the United Kingdom would still be the forestmost Super Power (if you can call it that) in the world, and we would have the continuance of the world balance of power as it had been since after 1815 (defeat of Napoleon) and 1848 (European revolutions put down). 
Indeed, as I understood the European situation, even before I read about Bismarck: the story of 1848-1945 is simply Germany’s challenge to the British World Order (or Anglo-American). It is the century of German rise and power. And despite the fact that the UK managed to defeat Germany in the end, the UK too, had exhausted itself in crushing the continental threat. Now, 1945 and onwards, it was time for a new world order, a new empire. And despite the USSR’s challenge to that empire, it came out on top and still strong. Though now with China, Iran, and Russia back at its doorstep, and idiots inside causing a mess, I wonder how its preeminent position in the world will hold up.</p>

<p>Let’s see how long the American World Order will last.</p>

<h3 id="part-ii">PART II</h3>
<h3 id="thoughts-on-bismarck-part-ii-july-30-2020">Thoughts on Bismarck Part II July 30 2020.</h3>
<p>After reading the Edgar Feuchtwanger book about Bismarck I have now a more defined view of Bismarck I think. First, that it is necessary to say that Bismark’s achievement in unifying Germany during his great period of 1860-1871 is something truly remarkable, and if it were not for said unification it is highly likely that Germany today would be two states: 1. North Germany, 2. Greater Bavaria (IE South Germany), split along the river Main. This would be due to the reasons I have discussed before: IE, Southern particularism, Catholicism, agriculturalism, and inherent dislike of Northern (especially Prussian) domination.</p>

<p>We may excuse Bismarck for his inherently undemocratic and unconstitutional actions during this period of 1860-1871, for it is the case that every founding of a nation is beset by moral problems upon which we now look with embarassement, shame, or disgust. So it is the case with Bismarck’s unification of Kleindeutschland (IE Little Germany: a Germany that does not include Austria, as opposed to Grossdeutschland, most famously realized by Hitler). Although during this period Bismarck employed many evil tactics, such as the threat of military action on social democrats, jailing opposition journalists, loud propoganda efforts, and efforts to split the opposition parties, we must also remember that he did not start any of these tactics: in fact they were in use before he came into power. Prussian militarism, censorship of the press, monarchical confrontation, were all tools of the long standing Hohenzollern Dynasty in Prussia. However, Bismarck CAN be blamed for aggravating the use of these tactics, for making it more widespread, for pushing it to the limit with his brinksmanship, for being confrontational and lying about his actions afterwards, or using the excuse that “he did it to surpress the danger that parliamentarism brings and its consequent revolutionary tendancies”. But even then, it is true that many other nations in their founding have done similar things.</p>

<p>Thus, it is not so much the era of 1860-1871 in which I find Bismarck evil and distasteful, but the period after 1871, in his long rule (comprising 2/3 of his time in office actually) over the Unified German Empire. After the unification of Germany, Bismarck has already achieved the seemingly unachieveable. At this point, Germany is very well set for the future: with a strong military, large population, a growing industrial-economic base, and political prestiege internationally (if not even evny and resentment). Yet despite these facts, Bismarck firmly clings to power and tries to surrppress the Social Democratic and parlimentary movement. Why does he continue to do these anti-socialist measures? It is hard to say. Whether or not Bismarck thinks democratic tendancies and socialism truly is bad is up for debate: but the fact remains that all his actions point towards the shoring up of his own position and power at the expense of other parties, most especially the Social Democrats. Indeed: the fact that he passed the health and age insurance laws does not necessarily mean that he truly thought these laws were a good thing: rather, it is more proveable that he thought by passing these laws he could get votes that would form a continued base of support for him.</p>

<p>Indeed, Bismarck never commits himself to one party, and he always tries to keep his own position. Riding off the wave of his amazing success in unification, Bismarck adopted the persona of the “State above politics” who is willing to do anything for the nation. (Obviously this tactic is often used by dictators and demagogues, just look at Trump). But in reality, what is the state IF NOT politics itself? People who claim to be neutral in politics deserve the lowest rung in hell. And indeed we see that Bismarck is VERY political. But not in the traditional conservative or liberal sense that we think today. Rather, he is political in always maintaing his own position. (Although it is true that he consistently tends to lean right rather than left).</p>

<p>One might say that Bismarck did these morally grey actions out of necessity, since he knew he was the only man who could maintain the system of delicate balance, of trust and fear, of alliance and counter alliance in Europe, of sitting on the fence between all nations. But this itself raises the question: if Bismarck knew how hard it was to play this international game, and that he had no good successors, why did he continue to play it? Obviously he knows he can’t live forever. Why didn’t he either simply declare German neutrality, or declare firmly for one side? The fact that Bismarck did not prepare anyone to be his successor, or did not set up the parliament so that it would be strong enough to combat William II’s arrogant and rash behavior is still a mystery to me. Was it really that he was so afraid of democracy and the spectre of European revolution that he did not, to his closing days in his position as chancellor, open up the forum to unhindered democratic discourse?</p>

<p>To the very end, he rode upon a semi-dictator system that he created and never once wanted to get off: though he was moderate in his war and unification aims in 1871, it is blatantly clear that he was never moderate in his sheer hunger for political power and personal political freedom: the freedom to do what HE wants, the freedom to tell everyone else to get in line. Although one might argue that this sort of action was most common to the monarchies of europe, it must be remembered that Bismarck presided over his semi-dictatorship during a period of national growth and the gradual beginning of a national German popular consciousness. The fact that the very first government this German consciousness grew up with was the semi-dictatorship of Bismarck must obviously have heavily tainted its political development and consciouesness. Perhaps the best thing Bismarck could have done to ensure the peaceful transfer of power and the continued functioning of politics was to either prepare a skilled succesor, or establish greater parliamentary powers, and then simply retire.</p>

<p>There are other things which Bismarck failed to address. Most noticeably: he did not realize the power of the rising industrial-urban proletariat, which quickly became a class of its own after the Unification of Germany. He also failed to realize that although the National German sentiment may be used to create Germany, he and future leaders might lose control of it after Germany had become established and grew proud and confident of its own abilities, thereafter forcing its will upon stupid, arrogant, egotistic, and easily swayed autocrats like William II. Public opinion was not simply a tool anymore, it would later become an end of its own, and to disasterous effect. If you pull a plant to make it grow “taller”, you kill its roots. In this sense Bismarck did the same: he built Germany so quickly and brilliantly that he did not notice that its political foundation was made of hay. It looks sturdy at first, but at the first strong wind the whole thing topples down.</p>

<p>Thus, I now revise my previous assessment, and I think that the saying that “Bismarck created a high power racing car that only he knew how to drive” is in fact quite accurate. But there is one question: if indeed Bismarck did somehow have a Chancellor-successor that was as skilled as he, could that new Chancellor have managed to deal with the growing national consciousness, sentiment and pride that Bismarck created in his Unification? We must remember that Bismarck was only able to get to his position of near-dictator because the time was right: the Kaiser William I was weak, the failed revolutions of 1848 had just happened, Germany was fragmented, Austria was overstretched, France was viewed with Suspicion. 
Thus it can be observed with great astonishment: that Bismarck not only occupied the position of the fulcrum in the world of domestic parliament vs monarch politics, in the world of foreign nation vs nation politics, but also in the historical timeline of the transition from Cabinet era diplomacy (Metternich Style) to National-popular diplomacy (Louis Napoleon [newphew of Napoleon I] Style). Bismarck used the people’s popular sentiment to create Unified Germany, but did not consequently give it the freedom and rights that should consequently follow (as happened in England and the United States).</p>

<p>THE CONTRADICTION: he created a National-Popular state, but ran it with a Cabinet-Ministry government.</p>

<p>Now one might argue that Bismarck thought the new country was not yet ready to become a more open democracy: that much like a bird who is learning to use its wings, if you let it go it might think too highly of itself and flap away and fall to the ground. But the fact remains that if Bismarck really thought the new country not ready: why did he not prepare the grounds, why did he not train the new government to fly on its own wings, without the help of papa Bisarck? It seems that ultimatley, Bismarck simply just did not like parliamentary democracy, and also he was just really power hungry. Time and again he said that the “British parliamentary system was not for Prussia/Germany”. From statements like these it becomes clear that what he has in mind for Germany is a dictator state with the nice-looking cloak of the Reichstag. But who is to be the dictator? Bismarck only.</p>

<p>We will never know what might have happened if Bismarck did step off the helm after the Unification of Germany in 1871. Perhaps socialist sentiment would have risen to such a degree as to scare the neighbor countries and cause some sort of “revolution repression” war. Though this seems unlikely: since France was already a national-populist state, and Austria had barely the funds and organization to defeat a unified Kleindeutschland. It is likely that if Bismarck had created a stronger constitutional and parliamentary framework, there would have been no WWI, given the fact that perhaps parliament would have been able to control William II and also resist the pressure of the German populace who wanted to go to war over their international prestiege. But again, this is debateable and unknown.</p>

<p>The concrete fact remains that Bismarck’s 28 years (in office) of secret and often shady dealings in both domestic and foreign affairs created a lasting legacy that the common citizen of Germany should simply let the “grown ups” do the hard work. As Feuchtwanger puts it: “Germany was always looking for a savior, especially after they had experienced Bismarck’s miraculous unification of Germany and his “above the politics” manner”. As we subsequently see in German history up to 1945, the German people are always thinking of the “good old days” and looking for a savior to lift them out of their international shame (most especially over the WWI war guilt clause).</p>

<p>Yet despite the people’s admiration for Bismarck they eventually felt that the country was stagnating under his policy: for he would not give up power and he would not allow for stronger parliament, nor would he allow for rapid colonial expansion or wars with Russia and France (things which the populace desired). It is thus highly ironic that the very national sentiment that Bismarck used to unify German and cement his position as Chancellor ended up kicking him out of office, as symbolized by the new emperor William II. For William II was a vain and easily hurt man, with a half-disabled left arm and parents who didn’t really like him, he was always looking for attention and validation. And what better place for an emperor to look for love and support and power than from his very own people? And what better act to gain the love of the people than to kick out a grumpy old minister who is overstaying his tenure in office, even if he is the unifier of Germany?</p>

<p>Even in retirement Bismarck couldn’t stop doing politics. He would constantly write articles for journals, in which he blasted the current state of affairs. He would always spurn William II in formal events, or simply not even go when invited. Now that he was kicked out of power by William II, he wrote that the “Reichstag needed to harbor a constant majority with which it is thereby enabled to criticize, control and warn the government”. Indeed, this sudden about-face from his previous statements about the very dangers of parliamentary government shows that he really doesn’t care: he just wants to be the one in charge. Everything is a means to him: the only ends are himself and the peace of Germany. But it is also true that he was right: a strong Reichstag was necessary to control William II, but it never materialized: thanks in large part to Bismarcks’ own 28 years of surrpressing it.</p>

<p>Thus, Bismarck had created a semi-dictatorial institution that functioned specifically on the fulcrum position the Chancellor held. But it is often forgotten that although the Chancellor held great power, he also was held in account for his actions: and could not simply do anything he wanted (since he was not emperor himself). For although Bismarck threatened the dissolution of the Reichstag many times, he knew that it was very dangerous to actually carry out such a threat: it would most likely risk civil war. Furthermore, he was still held marginally accountable to both emperor and parliament, despite often manipulating them. Thus it is interesting to imagine what Bismarck would have been like if he was NOT inhibited as Chancellor, for example, if he was actually emperor himself. Indeed, as history shows: the subsequent de-facto ruler of Germany, William II, had no such restraints: for he WAS the emperor. But then again, William II was also very arrogant, rash, and stupid.</p>

<p>Perhaps if Bismarck had retired in 1871 and convicned the militaristic and conservative William I to let parliament take over, there might have been a healing of internal wounds in Germany. Maybe the southern states would have really come into the fold, instead of the Kulturkampf that followed 1871 all the way to Bismarck’s fall. Perhaps Catholics would have learned to get along with protestants, industrialists with farmers, rich with the newly working poor, and so on. It is thus sad to see the maxim true: if you want to unite a people: go to war. Bismarck unified Germany economically, geographically, and militarily through the Austro-Prussian war and the Franco-Prussian war. And one might say that William II unified Germany culturally and politically through various acts of bravado, such as in grabbing colonies, cutting ties with the “Russian Slav race”, building a big fleet to rival Britain’s (which it never could rival Britain’s), and finally, in starting WWI. For indeed, there was never such a fervor as when war was declared in August of 1914. Never was there such a feeling of national, specifically GERMAN, unity and purpose. The time had come to defeat the decadent French, the scheming British, the slavish Russian, the insurgent Polish, who had all detested and envied German unification and power. What the world would have become if Imperial Germany had won, one can only imagine.</p>

<h3 id="the-big-picture-across-the-atlantic">The Big Picture across the Atlantic.</h3>
<p>Despite all these devlopments in Germany and on continental Europe, one must not think that WWI was the point when “Western History” (if there is even such a term) stepped into “Modernity” (if even such a term means anything). Indeed, the situation in Germany was merely a sideshow in the grand spectacle of Western History. For during the Unification of German from 1860-1871, there was an even greater event taking place across the Atlantic. From 1861-1865 there was a brutal civil war in the United States of America, where an internal kulturkampf of even greater proportions played out with the deaths of about 750,000 soldiers, 80,000 slaves, 50,000 civilians, and the total destruction of large swaths of the Southern states. For this was a war in which men fought not because they were greedy for more land, or more prestiege, or more power, or more resources, but rather, because they thought that each other’s way of life to be INHERENTLY incompatiable with their own, and fought to the DEATH over it. (It can even be distinguished from Napoleon’s invasion of Russia, since that was was one of political reasons: Napoleon wished to make Russia follow its political ends, that of adhereing to the Continental System of Embargo against Britain, whereas Russia wished to retain its independence of conduct and sovereignty.) In this light, the German wars of Unification are small and political matters in comparison to the all-out life and death struggle between the Union and the Confederacy.</p>

<p>Indeed, it is this AMERICAN war that, I think, is the step into modernity. For in it you see (for the first time in many instances) that railroads are used as weapons, that trenches become commonplace, that aimed rifle fire becomes standard infantry procedure, that fortified civilian centers and their consequent bombardment become commonplace, that the entire nation becomes a resource to be used in the defeat of the enemy, that there unconditional surrender is the only option, that scorched Earth is a viable offensive strategy, that ways of life that are at war, that the entire population is at war.</p>

<h4 id="the-impresiveness-of-the-german-achievement">The impresiveness of the German achievement.</h4>
<p>Again, when one looks at the bigger picture one realizes the smallness of the German achievement. Little Germany rose and fell within a span of 47 years (1871-1918). Weimar lasted 15 years (1918-1933). Nazi Germany lasted 12 years (1933-1945). Whereas America is still here. But perhaps it is precisely because of Germany’s smallness that its achievements are still something so dazzling today. Despite being a tiny little nation, Prussia managed to defeat Austria. Despite being a fragmented coalition, North Germany and its Southern allies managed to defeat France. Despite having to carry its weak-ass neighbor Austria, Imperial Germany managed to kick Russia out of WWI and almost killed France. And 20 years later, even after disarmarment and a decade of economic failure, Germany in its Nazi form STILL managed to nearly take over all of Europe. Even today, despite partition and the numerous economic and social mechanisms created by the allies to keep Germany economically reliant on its neighbors, it is yet again, the most powerful country in Europe: with the most advanced weapons, the biggest industry, the most developed economy, and the most exports: surpassed only by China and the United States. Indeed, I think it is this consistent underdog status and meteoric rise of Germany that keeps historians and civilians alike fascinated with its history, culture, and legacy (for good and bad), and politicians fearful of its explosive potential. Only time will tell what the future holds for Germany on the world stage. Will it continue to be an abiding member of the EU, competing economically and trying to save its pathetic allies (most especially Greece)? Or will it take the lead once more and form a Pan-European state, capable of filling the void of American leadership, capable of competing with China, capable of standing up to Russian encroachment? All I know is this: that as much as I desire peace and prosperity, it is the sad and shameful fact for a historian that it is usually trying and turbulent times that make for the best reading.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First written: 2020 July 4-30.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Masks of War</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/24/The-Masks-of-War.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Masks of War" /><published>2022-11-24T08:11:11+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-24T08:11:11+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/24/The-Masks-of-War</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/24/The-Masks-of-War.html"><![CDATA[<p>First written 2022-08-09</p>

<p>In Carl H Builder’s “The Masks of War”, the author’s basic premise is that each of the three big armed forces branches of the United States have their own institutional personalities.</p>

<p>A comparison at the start of the book sums up the three branches very aptly:<br />
The Army’s modest, stone block, colorless, old chapel.<br />
The Navy’s ostentatious, tall, large, with a big dome, decked with deep blue carpets chapel. <br />
The Air Forces’ modern, soaring, silver walls lined with shining stained glass, space-ship like chapel.</p>

<p>The Army is the nation’s loyal servant, courageous, quiet, dutiful, all encompassing in its efforts to make do with what materials and manpower it is given to do the job it is given. Out of all three branches, the army is most cooperative with the nation and with the other two branches, for it understands that without air support and sea lift it cannot get to the places it needs to fight. The army is also the branch with the greatest legitimacy and the least innovation, stemming from the fact that it draws from the common citizenry. This legitimacy also stems from the fact that the army is the one who sustains the vast majority of human casualties in wartime.</p>

<p>The army prides itself on the art of war, rather than the technology of war, although Builder states that in recent years, the army is becoming more and more addicted to “toys”. The army is also the branch that most suffers from a disconnect between what it wants to do and what it most likely will be called upon to do. The army envisions itself as a mass land force combating America’s enemies (this self conception is a result of its glorious victory in Europe 1945), but the advent of nuclear weapons has largely deterred war between competing industrialized nuclear states. Instead, as we have seen, the army is far more likely to be called into “third world combat zones” in order to assert American interests. One thinks of Korea, Vietnam, Panama, Kuwait, Afghanistan, Iraq, and so on. These are clearly not glorious wars (with the exception of Kuwait), and consequently the army is having a hard time admitting and adjusting to the fact that limited wars are becoming the norm.</p>

<p>In all these combat zones, the most useful arm of the Army (apart from the Kuwait War) was the infantry. But the army is loathe to reduce its desire for big artillery and fancy tanks, since it views intelligence gathering, guerrilla training, local suppression, and slogging through hard terrain as un-glamorous. But this is exactly the problem: high tech weapons can only defeat high tech enemies: cruise missiles killing terrorist leaders does not stop the local populace from rebelling or aiding the terrorists. Out of all his predictions, Builder was most correct to point out the problem of the Army: Afghanistan, Iraq, all displayed the inability of the army to 1. suppress rebellions and 2. create loyal and effective local institutions. Part of this failure was because Congress did not want America to create governments (as that is seen as anti-democratic), but only to help in “policing”, but part of this failure was also because the Army simply did not and still does not have the ability to police people; because it does not want to see itself in that un-glamerous way.</p>

<p>The Army, thus, is stuck in a strategic quagmire, because it refuses to let go of its idealized image of itself: still reminiscing over the glory days of 1944-1945 Europe.</p>

<p>The Navy is the most independent of the three branches: it is proud, haughty, skilled, and totally aware of what forces it needs to do the job at hand (or at least, the job it wants to do). The tradition and haughtiness of the Navy was so strong that even up until the 1970s high commanding officer’s land quarters were assigned servants and housekeepers. The independent streak of the navy stems from the old problem of command and control in the era before radio: navy commanders were often given full control of their ships and their mens’ lives. (Think back to Perry, who was commander, president, diplomat, and warlord, making all the decisions on the spot by himself, to sail into Japanese waters and threaten them.) It is this long standing traditional operational independence that informs the Navy’s staunch efforts to resist any attempt by any party to encroach on its area of influence.</p>

<p>The Navy is in between the army and air force in terms of its strategic innovation and legitimacy. Although the common people can understand the Navy’s use, they do not understand why the Navy so highly values its independence. The Navy’s strategic thinking is also in the middle because its strategy can only change so fast as its ships change: although a fully primed war industry can build a plane or tank relatively quickly, a ship still needs a long while to build. Thus, out of all three branches, the Navy focuses most on how to use their ships, rather than what ships should be built. But despite the long build period for ships, this doesn’t mean the Navy has an excuse to not ask what kind of war it will most likely be fighting in the future.</p>

<p>Currently, the Navy’s choice self perception is still the “big ships open sea” doctrine, as best represented by the entire naval campaign against Imperial Japan in the pacific. Although carriers have replaced battleships as the capitol ships, nonetheless, the emphasis is on big surface ships in big formations fighting a worthy enemy navy in big formation. Of course, as you may have noticed, and as I have (and am) predicting in my earlier posts, there is nothing saying that an adversary has to fight the US navy in the way that the US navy wants them to fight.</p>

<p>And furthermore, statistics show that big fleet battle is not the all-deciding factor. Although we often hear that the carrier battle at Midway was the turning point in the Pacific, one rarely hears of the huge contribution American submarines made in sinking Japanese convoys. In fact, 2% of America’s seagoing personnel (the submariners) accounted for a whopping 55% of Japanese convoy tonnage sunk. If the battle for islands such as Okinawa and Iwo Jima was brutal enough, imagine how much worse it would have been if the Japanese garrisons were actually well supplied and well fed!</p>

<p>And speaking of convoys, the US Navy loathes to put more money into convoy escort. This is because the Navy sees convoy escort duty as un-glamorous and boring. (Think how for all the movies about Carrier and even Submarine warfare in WW2, the only one about escort warfare that comes to mind is Tom Hank’s recent “Greyhound”, which wasn’t even released in theaters: this just goes to show how unpopular even in the public’s mind the duty of convoy escort is). Yet as I have described, it was precisely the lack of convoy escort on the part of the Japanese that crippled their oceanic empire. Likewise, it was precisely the lack of effective convoy escort (during the early ears of the war) across the Atlantic that nearly starved the British isles.</p>

<p>In the next conflict, it is likely that no one will be dumb enough to challenge the USN on the high seas, instead, it would be much more effective (as Hitler realized) to target Allied shipping by using submarines. (And submarines are super effective: in an exercise in 2005, a Swedish submarine utilizing an ultra quiet engine “sank” an American carrier being screened by friendly destroyers). Also, the current USN’s fixation on high seas fleet battle and littoral invasion (as evidenced by the stupid investments into the Zumwalt destroyers and the USS Freedom/USS Independence) will likely not come to much if any use in the future, given the fact that an invasion of any adversarial nation with nuclear weapons would inevitably invite worldwide nuclear destruction, and that any invasion of a third world power would likely not require such intense littoral support. Instead, it would be prudent for the USN to invest in more destroyer escorts and long range naval aircraft patrol planes.</p>

<p>The air force is the wonder child of the military. It was born purely out of theory, and put into action by the sheer ingenuity of humanity’s combined intellect. Therefore, out of all three branches, the air force is least attached to either nation or institution. The air force exists because its people love to fly: they love their machines, they love to be in the air, they love to push the boundaries. War is secondary to them, flying is the primary concern. For example, how many of you watched the new Top Gun? Many people said it was not American military propaganda. But that is just a surface analysis: even if their claim was true, why did they go watch it? Because of fascination and addiction to those incredible machines which propel one through the air, a medium in which humans clearly are not supposed to be in! And it is exactly the fact that people are so enamored with the aspect of flying and the skill required to pull it off that the air force is able to garner new recruits, scientists, and engineers to their cause. So in fact, it is military propaganda, since the air force is not an institution per se, but a band of pilots who love their machines and the sky, bankrolled by the US government, with the justification for public consumption that they may one day be called up to fight in the sky.</p>

<p>Out of all three branches, the air force has the least legitimacy, since it can easily be argued that their job is to simply make sure enemy air power doesn’t cripple allied ships and divisions. And that job doesn’t require an independent air branch. Thus, historically, the air force has always based its reason for existing as an independent branch under centralized control on one major concept: strategic bombing. This is because strategic bombing as a concept is completely independent from the other two branches, and glorifies the air force as an independent wing able to end wars by bombing the enemy nation to bits. Never-mind the fact that the evidence for strategic bombing is not conclusive, or that missiles have largely replaced strategic bombers; the air force still insists on this doctrine because it is the only doctrine which gives it a reason for independent existence.</p>

<p>For example, look at the performance of the B-52 bomber during the Vietnam war: not only did they not achieve much, but also their rate of attrition due to Vietnamese SAM defense sites was alarmingly high. During World War 2 as well, the use of strategic bombers neither totally destroyed German and Japanese war industry, nor did it compel them to surrender: the Germans surrendered only after the Soviets were literally in Berlin, and the Japanese surrendered only after it was guaranteed that their emperor would be allowed to remain. Of course, strategic bombers played an important part, but it is hard for an outsider analyst to conclude that this justified the enormous expenditure on bombers, crews, airfields, oil, payloads, along with separate independent command, and so on, much less to conclude that strategic bombing alone carried the day.</p>

<p>The continued advocacy for strategic bombing exists in part also because of nuclear weapons. However, even with the advent of the B-2 Bomber, it is clear that cost and maintenance of this flying wing wonder is grossly disproportional when compared to its strategic nuclear and general-combat roles. That is to say, is its main job to drop nukes? If so, it isn’t worth the money compared to ICBMs and SSBNs, nor is the wing nearly as survivable. Or, if it’s main job is to drop long range precision bombs, then other aircraft can do that for much cheaper, and we could afford to lose those other aircraft too, while a loss of even a single B-2 would be devastating (there are less than 20 in operation, and they contain some of the most secret technology). My suspicion is that the DOD has allowed the air force to retain a small amount of B-2s as a gesture of goodwill, in the hopes of better future cooperation. Otherwise, alienating one major branch of the military would not be good.</p>

<p>The least favorite activity of the air force has always been air-ground support: since it relegates the pilot to the role of secondary actor in the stage of ground warfare. Furthermore, ground support duty also means that the pilot cannot fly free in the sky to fight other pilots, and it also means that the pilot must obey the directives of the air support controller on the ground. The air force’s antipathy to ground support is most noticeable by a quick examination of its inventory: only a single plane (the A-10 Warthog) is designed from the ground up to carry out ground support missions. All other USAF planes, especially the notoriously cost-overrun F-35, have air superiority as their primary role and ground support as a conciliating secondary role for the other branches of service (otherwise DOD would never approve those planes). Yet, unlike strategic bombing’s iffy track record, it can be proven that air-ground support was key in numerous battles in World War 2: Nazi Maneuver Warfare doctrine, Soviet Deep Battle doctrine, and American Overwhelming Firepower doctrine all relied on and effectively used decisive air-ground support to win battles.</p>

<p>Despite the air force’s current distaste for air-ground support, it is likely that air-ground support will be vital in future wars in third world countries, given their (usually) horrible infrastructure and difficult terrain. As we have already seen in Korea, Vietnam, and Afghanistan, it is very difficult to deploy armor and heavy artillery in such unforgiving geography and low development areas. Air-ground support, which can bypass hills and jungles by flying over them, then, will be the key.</p>

<p>All in all, it seems to me that the greatest risk we have is the in ability of the army to switch to an infantry-focused doctrine. This is because war with other major industrialized powers, although “glorious”, is not likely, due to the prevalence of nuclear weapons and the logic of indefinite nuclear escalation in the situation of a losing war (for whichever side). (Of course, this also assumes American politics is not insane and the country doesn’t try to look for a scapegoat in some other major power). Also, it would not be useful to push into the homeland of an adversarial great power who is armed with nukes, since doing so would force them into a corner, thus prompting a nuke launch.</p>

<p>As Builder noticed in the 1990s, the army is also starting to get addicted to “toys”, like the air force and navy are addicted. Just recently, we have witnessed the huge revamp in infantry rifles with the 277 fury cartridge and complementary battle rifle. Although such a rifle definitely prioritizes the infantry, without adequate training, logistics, intelligence gathering, and so on as discussed above, such a rifle is only a new toy to play with, and cannot accomplish the necessary tasks needed for third-world warfare and policing. Indeed, such a rifle is more suited to fighting body-armored enemy infantry, rather than run-and-hide terrorists groups.</p>

<p>The second greatest risk is the navy, who is still hankering for littoral combat ships and carriers, instead of the lowly and trusty destroyer. Indeed, it was only after a long development and trial period that the navy finally realized that the Zumwalt stealth destroyer concept was too cost inefficient; also, the Zumwalt’s main cannon used a special ammo that was very hard to source. Recently, if I remember correctly, they are once again returning to upgrading and producing more of the classic Arleigh Burke class destroyers.</p>

<p>The air force is likely to remain in its current posture simply because of institutional pressure and friction. There is no major reason for them to change, so they probably won’t: they fulfill their current job of air superiority well enough, and that’s all the DOD is really looking for at this point. Even though better air-ground support planes would be good for the army, the air force likely will not make any steps towards this venture, given no urgent need. However, it is interesting to point out that the reason the air force generals in my previous post (Status of US Strategic Weapons) argued for a continued nuclear bomber presence was by saying that “sure bombers are less cost effective and survivable than ICBMs and the new submarine nuclear missiles, but by having a trinity of delivery systems we can force the Soviets to spend a proportionately more amount of resources into defending against bombers”. Again, the reasoning was one of trading costs with the Soviets, but in reality, the Air officers simply wanted to make sure their domain of strategic bombing remained relevant.</p>

<p>Interestingly enough, a sub branch of the Navy, the Marine Corps, is in fact evolving towards a direction that makes ample sense. The MC have rid themselves of any main battle tanks, and are returning to their role of amphibious assault (which is traditionally very infantry intensive). Indeed, it seems that after 20 years in Afghanistan, the Marine Corps have finally managed to shake off their use by the military as a first strike force for all purposes (note how they were constantly deployed in the middle east, despite the entire region lacking any real need for amphibious assault), and are now returning to their role as a first strike force for amphibious assaults only.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First written 2022-08-09]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One Beautiful Spring Day - Jim Woodring (2022)</title><link href="https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/20/One-Beautiful-Spring-Day.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Beautiful Spring Day - Jim Woodring (2022)" /><published>2022-11-20T08:58:58+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-20T08:58:58+00:00</updated><id>https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/20/One-Beautiful-Spring-Day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://william6542.github.io//2022/11/20/One-Beautiful-Spring-Day.html"><![CDATA[<p>Finished 2022-11-15. 
First posted 2022-11-20.</p>

<p>One Beautiful Spring Day by Jim Woodring is a ‘book’? ‘Graphic novel’? ‘Fantasy tale’? ‘Odyssey’? ‘Painting of reality’? ‘LSD’ trip? ‘Dream’? ‘Nightmare’? It is hard to say what ISBN-13 978-1683965886 really is. First, justice must be done to the insane squiggly lines of filler and shade that Woodring uses to fill space, denote shadow, and otherwise create forms and shapes of terrifying and mesmerizing proportions. The contrast between what is familiar and what is grotesque permeates the entire story, and while you may be lulled into a sense of security with Frank and the pups, it is inevitable that you will soon be drawn into a panel with unceasing horror. Woodring’s art is spectacular and complex, beautiful and trippy, understandable and also un-understandable, all at the same time.</p>

<p>So, what is the tldr summary of this book, or to fill out a metadata element: what is it about, (really?)? Whereas ‘The Frank Book’ is a collection of tales with a Aesop-like quality in tone and length, One Beautiful Spring day is a continuous 400 page epic. Perhaps it may most easily be described as one anthromorphic being’s experience of life: the insanity and reality of life. Any other description, though maybe more accurate and detailed, would fall short in describing what the entire book is ‘about’.</p>

<p>However, some major themes of the book can be seen in the book’s few whole-page and two-page panels. One of the most prominent whole-page panels is Frank sleeping on his divan-recliner-ottoman-sofa chair at home.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/TwoFranksSleeping.jpg" alt="Frank Sleeping Compare" /></p>

<p>These two panels appear at different points in the book, but with minor variations. In both panels Frank is content, resting during midday. The weather must be warm since his window is open and he isn’t blanketed. Yet all is not well. In both scenes, the hot air balloon outside the window causes chaos and disaster for Frank when it drops random stuff on Frank’s lawn, and Frank opens those items and uses them, which causes destruction. So while it may be said that the balloon brings disaster, it is Frank and his foolishness that makes the disaster real.</p>

<p>But the most noticeable difference is the additional presence of a thick book on the stand in the second rendition of this scene. This may be a clever play on the reader’s activity, given that 240 is just past the middle of the book, and comes at a lull or ‘reset’ in the book’s story. I found myself setting the book down at this point, as it was getting late. Reality reflected fiction. Indeed, the fact that the bookmark is also at the midpoint of Frank’s book suggests that the book, or ‘life’ he is ‘reading’ is the same book that we are reading too.</p>

<p>But, the other significance of the book is clearly not played out by Frank: a book’s signifacance as knowledge. As one reads on past page 240, it becomes clear that Frank has not learned anything. If there is one thing that is similar thematically between The Frank Book and One Beautiful Spring Day, it is that Frank is ever the Fool. So while Frank’s home has all the symbols of civilization, order, and continuity of knowledge, Frank himself exhibits surprisingly little continuity or rememberance. Rather, his home is what anchors him, not himself.</p>

<p>Another small change is the slight degredation of the flowers. Despite the presence of a watering can, it is likely he has not watered the plants in a while. But is that a fault of his? He has spent the past 100+ pages away from his home, a home which was destroyed early on in the story, mind you. So if this is the only damage the home exhibits after its miraculous reappearance around page 230+, is it really any damage at all?</p>

<p>Although lifeless objects and structures are destroyed and reconstitute themselves off page, living beings in this book are usually never restored to their normal state. The balloon rider becomes crippled, the horse-man thing forever remains faceless, Jivas are ripped apart, monsterous animals and aggresive plant life are sliced apart by Frank, and Fran completley obliterates two creepy male creatures trying to block her way.</p>

<p>Yet Frank himself is essentially invulnerable. One time his arm and leg gets bitten off, yet they regenerate (he even seems surprised). Another time he breaks his own skull and his soul flies out, but it returns and he reawakens with no scars. He falls through black space and does not freeze, he squeezes through a tiny hole and suffers no damage, he is beatup by manhog, suffers starvation, experiences heartbreak (twice), and gets smashed at high speeds against jagged rock while driving a world-car.</p>

<p>A few other characters also exhibit elements of invulnerability: Fran is a eldritch god, Whim is whim, and Pupshaw and Pushpaw are also undestroyable. However, for Frank and the two pups, it isn’t clear if their invulnerability would hold out if they weren’t rescued at certain points by each other.</p>

<p>Perhaps this is the lie that our own consciousness tells us: that whatever horrors may happen to us, that whatever sadness or evil we will experience, that we will always come out whole again, alive. For Frank always seems to come out alive through the most impossible of mechanisms. Perahps it is this life which is a dream, a dream in which we ignore the steaming train about to rush us over.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/FrankAndTrain.jpg" alt="Frank and Train" /></p>

<p>This scene is not actually in the book, but is included in the limited edition as a signed print. It also seems that Woodring may have intended this to be included in the book during his drafts, but ultimatley chose to not do so. Anyways.</p>

<p>How is Frank still alive in this two-page panel? Clearly the train is active, but there is no sign of momentum. Also, Whim is sitting on the top calmly, which futher suggests the train is still. Or is it the line of Pupshaws that are protecting Frank? Pupshaw (as shown in other scenes) is a minor god, with superhuman strength and durability. But how to explain so many of Pupshaws? Furthermore, why is Frank even sleeping on the tracks anyway? The two pups are definitley Frank’s friends, but they are also his pets, they are his guardians, and in some scenes they even act as his servants. It’s never clear why they act in these capcities. While Pushpaw’s love and loyalty towards Frank may be explained as an extension of his first love and loyalty towards Pupshaw, it is totally unclear why Pupshaw displays such love and loyatly towards Frank. The first fable in The Frank Book in which Pupshaw appears, when she is bought, liberated, and loved by Frank (as a pet), doesn’t seem very convincing as an answer. If she is a minor god, how was she taken in by the likes of the Pyramid-Chicken-Salesman to begin with?</p>

<p>But yet, here she is, guarding and smiling at Frank. Pushpaw too, smiles and looks askew, but is he looking at Frank, or at the darling of his life, Pupshaw? Perhaps, one may surmise a cliche take: that it is love and loyalty which keeps us alive, insulates us from the inevitableness that is ‘us hurtling towards death’ (or in this case death hurtling towards us), gives us the hope that we may yet not die. ‘Though one (an adversary perhaps, an assailant, death?) may prevail against him, two can withstand him, and a threefold chord is not quickly broken’. Yet despite proclaiming the benefits of having many friends, even this ancient saying does not guarantee that the ‘chord’ will not inevitably one day shatter.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/OBSDendPage1.jpg" alt="color end page tuba" /></p>

<p>Indeed, it is often his two pups who get Frank into trouble as much as get him out of it. In the above color end page (which is a page within the main narrative), Pushpaw blows on a magical tuba dropped by the hot air balloon man. Out of the three who attempted to blow the horn, Frank and Pupshaw both failed to create a ‘bubble’ entity large enough to sustain itself in the air. But Pushpaw manages to blow so hard that this swarming biblically correct angel manifests and maintains itself.</p>

<p>What is this angel? Turns out, inside is a bunch of Pupshaw-Pushpaw esque babies! Super cute! The two go inside to meet their ‘family’ and decide to stay. Frank, trying to join them, is prevented when the mouth/staircase of the angel breaks off. Left behind, Frank goes home in sadness. If the bond between Frank and his two pups is so strong, why would they so easily abandon him? Is the book suggesting that the pups have consciousness, that they have created their own world in which they wish to inhabit? Do we as owners have the right to chain our pets to us? What if they wish to wander free?</p>

<p>Whatever the case, their lack is immediately effected upon Frank when he is unable to fend off a flowery horse which bites off two of his limbs. Luckily, him and manhog are eventually able to work together to fend it off, in the process becoming friends. So again, the idea that there must be a chord is shown. Indeed, even later, when the pups return into the narrative, and man-hog is ungracuously kicked out again, man-hog finds his own chord with two other ugly man-hogs.</p>

<p>…</p>

<p>I’ll end my thoughts here. It’s starting to get incoherent. It’s difficult to write a wholistic essay for this book, because despite being one epic, its story is segmented in a way that doesn’t lend to wholistic analysis. The book must be read as a whole, but it can only be analyzed in parts. I’m certain I can get more out of it by analyzing and documenting all the specific instances of when a reoccuring event happens, but I’m too lazy to do it now.</p>

<p>####Things to document for later essays:</p>
<ol>
  <li>All the panels in which Frank does the two hands up pose.</li>
  <li>All the whole-page and two-page panels.</li>
  <li>Each instance of dream transition, and the layers of dreams/locations Frank is in.</li>
  <li>The Fran story in detail, and her progression / reveal as an eldritch god.</li>
  <li>All the panels in which the keyhole appears.</li>
  <li>All the instances of self awareness (world-car, Woodring’s cabin, mirror museum, small new house in Fran’s house), p40 and 240.</li>
  <li>Apperances of man-hog and the constant change in his relationship with Frank.</li>
  <li>The actual amount of days this book takes place over, and the amount of days including dream/false sequences.</li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Finished 2022-11-15. First posted 2022-11-20.]]></summary></entry></feed>